<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Trodden dovvn strength, by the God of strength, or, Mrs Drake revived. Shewing her strange and rare case, great and many uncouth afflictions, for tenne yeares together : together, with the strange and wonderfull manner how the Lord revealed himselfe unto her, a few dayes before her death. / Related by her somtime unworthy friend, Hart On-Hi.</title>
            <author>Hart, John, D.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1156_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204874</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864329</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864329</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116556</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116556)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 251:E1156[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Trodden dovvn strength, by the God of strength, or, Mrs Drake revived. Shewing her strange and rare case, great and many uncouth afflictions, for tenne yeares together : together, with the strange and wonderfull manner how the Lord revealed himselfe unto her, a few dayes before her death. / Related by her somtime unworthy friend, Hart On-Hi.</title>
                  <author>Hart, John, D.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 193, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Bishop for Stephen Pilkington, and are to be sold at his Shop next to the Red-lyon Inne in Fleet-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Hart On-Hi = John Hart.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf bears a permission to print.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 25. 1646"; the 7 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Drake, Joan, 17th cent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116556:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TRODDEN DOWN STRENGTH, BY THE GOD OF STRENGTH, OR, M<hi rend="sup">RS</hi> 
               <hi>DRAKE</hi> REVIVED.</p>
            <p>SHEWING Her ſtrange and rare CASE, great and many uncouth Afflictions, for tenne yeares together: <hi>Together,</hi> With the ſtrange and wonderfull manner how the Lord revealed himſelfe unto her, a few dayes be ore her death.</p>
            <p>Related by her ſomtime unworthy friend, HART ON-HI.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 66.16.</bibl>
               <p>Come and heare, all yee that feare God; and I will declare what he hath done for my ſoule.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Biſhop</hi> for <hi>Stephen Pilkington,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop next to the Red-lyon Inne in Fleet-Street, 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116556:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Novemb.</hi> 12. 1646.</head>
            <p>I Have peruſed this Diſcourſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Drakes</hi> dangerous ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and feareful deſertions, with her bleſſed recovery, and joyfull iſſue out of all her troubles; and think it well worthy to be Printed and publiſhed, as a ſingular antidote to preſerve others in her conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from being plunged into and quite ſwallowed up with deep de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Downame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:116556:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116556:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116556:3"/>
            <p>TO THE MEMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE OF THAT EVER MEMORABLE MERCY SHEWED UNTO THAT LATE WORTHY GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WOMAN OF FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOVS MEMORY <hi>Mrs IOANE DRAKE</hi> IN ESCAPING SATANS MANY MIGHTY AND IN SHEW INVINCIBLE TEMPTATIONS.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116556:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116556:4"/>
            <head>TRODDEN DOWNE STRENGTH, OR, MRS <hi>DRAKE</hi> REVIVED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE matchleſſe rare <hi>Caſe,</hi> and in that kinde un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralleld trouble of that ſometime worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Ioan Drake</hi> of famous memory, wife of <hi>Francis Drake</hi> late of <hi>Eſher</hi> Eſquire; with the glorious and ſtrange concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord made with her, (I believe the like never read nor heard of) was the cauſe of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116556:5"/>this enſuing diſcourſe. Whoſe <hi>Caſe</hi> and trouble of ten years continuance being ſo rare and ſeldome met with; for that the Relation thereof might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps help ſome hard-hearted mourning Creatures hereafter, to gather heart and ſtrength, not to deſpaire (how deſperate ſoever their Caſe may ſeeme ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to themſelves or others to be) I have therefore by Gods help, and for the comfort of ſuch, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to ſet down here, for the glory of God, and confuſion of Satan (her maine ſtrong enemy) her <hi>Caſe,</hi> and cauſe thereof, with the progreſſe and iſſue of all, as briefly as poſſibly I could, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as a pertuall monument whilſt time laſts, of Gods great goodneſſe and infinite mercies even to the moſt hard-hearted and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116556:5"/>miſerable that may be. To the end, that as it was ſaid by <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Iob</hi> and his <hi>Caſe, Behold the Patience of</hi> Job, <hi>and what end the Lord made;</hi> ſo it may likewiſe hereafter be ſaid of this good woman, <hi>Behold the hardneſſe of heart, ſtiffneſſe and ſtoutneſſe of</hi> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Drake <hi>for a long time rejecting all meanes in a long continuance, and what a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble end the Lord made with her.</hi> Wherefore it being a diſcourſe full of windings and turnings, fraught with many of Satans ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties and intricate multifarious tentations, wherein <hi>Proteus</hi> like, he according unto the occaſion, changed ſhapes, to have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown this good Gentlewoman; all the ends whereof cannot (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the variety and ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) eaſily be knit together: I doe entreat the Readers patience
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116556:6"/>to beare with me, if ſometimes I ſeeme to looſe my ſelfe, or be too tedious, or for want of memory and multiplicity of matter be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced ſometimes to bring <hi>Hyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Proteron:</hi> But howſoever the buſineſſe, if largely related, might fill up a very great volumne, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend only as I am able, to gather together ſome of the moſt ſpeciall materiall things, knitting them as briefly as may be together; ſeeing by Gods mercy I was made an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Inſtrument of her recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and an eye-witneſſing Actor in all her <hi>Tragick-Comedy:</hi> (Not daring but to erect this Trophee of eternall thankfulneſſe for her) in imitation of former Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies in their deliverances; I was enforced and durſt not but thus vent the buſineſſe of her rare <hi>Caſe,</hi> unto ſucceeding Poſterity.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116556:6"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, we will ſhew <hi>how ſhee was ſet upon and aſſaulted in the night with fear and horror,</hi> with her fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going diſpoſition, character, and what fore-runners uſhered this her diſtemper which raiſed ſo great a ſtorme.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>By what ſtrange meanes, and way, the Lord made the Relater an unworthy Inſtrument, to have compaſsion on her, and finde her out,</hi> helping to furniſh her with the Inſtrument and means of her recovery; and what entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhee gave that meanes at his firſt comming unto her, and after, untill the time that ſhee revealed the Devils counſell, was contented to live, and uſe the meanes having any hope to be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Her deportment and carrige from this fornamed time, untill a little before her death.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116556:7"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, <hi>The preparation unto her death, with the ſtrange manner how the Lord revealed himſelfe unto her,</hi> before the ſame, the like never heard of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, ſhee was the daughter of that worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>William Totle</hi> Eſquire, one of the ſix Clerks of Chancery, his only Heire apparant, being likely to have enjoyed all his fortunes which were very great, according whereunto ſhee had all the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent breeding, which is uſuall, and befitted a Gentlewoman iſſued from ſuch worthy Parents, whoſe too great indulgence towards her in her youth (by her own confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) occaſioned ſo much ſorrow unto her in her riper years, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving then no correction at all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter.</note> Shee was of a low well compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtature, of a lovely browne
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116556:7"/>complexion, having a full nimble quick Sparrow-hawke eye, of a naturall joviall conſtitution, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally melancholy, full of love, curteſie, mercy and meekneſſe, affable in converſation, with a deep and nimble quick pleaſant preſent wit, tender-hearted, free and bountifull, in nothing covetous but of grace: the freeſt alive from all hypocriſie, unleſſe it were to bely her ſelf, wearing her worſt ſide outmoſt, being plaine, true and tender open-hearted, modeſt, eaſily drawn with love and good words; but if oppoſed, ſtout, ſtern and inflexible, uſing the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward contentments of the times, yet in a very indifferent, modeſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive way, reſolute in her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, valewing even then reall goodneſſe where ſhee ſaw it in any without hypocriſie,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116556:8"/>deteſting ſhewes without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: though then ſhee were not acquainted with the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, yet had ſhee it in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where ſhe ſaw it ſhine forth; ſo as though ſometimes in a little mirth, ſhe would vex and jeſt with the ſuppoſed worſer ſort, who at good times came to her of her neighbours; yet thoſe who were in her judgement right, ſhe uſed thus farre to open her ſelfe unto her waiting woman touching them, in this ſtrange preſaging manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doeſt thou ſee theſe people, ſome of whom I doe ſo jeare at and vex? of my conſcience I ſhall one day ere I die, bee one of them; for thoſe of them who are right, are the only happy ſouls,</hi> which was a ſtrange prediction of her (even then when ſhee was ſo farre from, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116556:8"/>unto them) as afterwards it came to paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Cauſe of her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</note> Gods providence, and her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents pleaſure, appointed unto her a Match, but ſuch a one (thought he was a worthy fine Gentleman of good birth, parts and fortunes) yet whom at firſt ſhee could not affect, ſo as ſhe was married againſt her will (a great Over-ſight in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) which firſt bred in her the foundation of thoſe ſtormes and tempeſts, which in time were in danger to have overthrown her. Wherein though ſhee were obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and dutifull unto her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; yet it ſtuck cloſe unto her, though her ſtrength of ſpirit and joviall temper endeavoured with all her ſtrength to have ſhaken it off, out-worn it, and by all meanes to have out-faced it, without ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of diſcontent, by merry
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116556:9"/>company and divers journeyes (which uſually divert melancholy thoughts) as though there had been no ſuch matter. But griefe being like unto fire, which though for a time ſmothered, yet could not long bee concealed, her diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s did ſecretly work upon her a habit of ſadneſſe in midſt of her mirth with her friends, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhewes than <hi>even in laughter the heart may be ſad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Cauſe of her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper.</note>About this time not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her marriage ſhe was brought to bed of a daughter (a dear daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unto her) becauſe in that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very being much wronged by her Midwiffe, ſhee was ever after troubled with fumes and ſcurvie vapors mounting up unto her head, which bred in her for the moſt part a continuall head-ach, like unto a megrum, together with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116556:9"/>ſomewhat like unto a fire continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally burning at her ſtomack, which no phyſick could remove, or was not Gods pleaſure it ſhould; the which drew her towards a more conſtant conſtitution of ſadneſſe and diſtemper, though yet with her uſuall ſtrength of ſpirit and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpoſition, ſhee out-faced, as though all had been well. But a fire of diſcontent being kindled full of ſad thoughts in her; which bred and encreaſed all the time ſhe lay in of her daughter; thus ſhortly after it fell out, That</p>
            <p>Her Father and Mother being very indulgent towards her in this Caſe, and both of them being with her, when at a time ſhe was ill at her Houſe at <hi>Eſher</hi> in <hi>Surrey;</hi> her Mother to comfort and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en her up, then lying one night with her; It came to paſſe that in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116556:10"/>the fore-part of the night ſhee fell aſleep, but not long after fell out into terrible ſhricks &amp; out-cryes, to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">The firſt grand tempeſt ſhee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured.</note> that <hi>ſhee was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, undone, ſhee was damned, and a caſt away, and ſo of neceſsity muſt needs goe to Hell, and therewith ſhook, dropt down with ſweat, and wept exceedingly:</hi> Wherewith her good Mother <hi>Mrs Totle</hi> much troubled, being a very religious tender-hearted Gentlewoman, did give her many good and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table exhortations, to be quiet, to truſt in God; not to believe illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, telling her, that <hi>the Devill was a liar,</hi> and ſo fell a praying with her,<note place="margin">A ſtrange change.</note> ſhee being in ſhew well recovered and pacified. Which being paſt, ſhe fell aſleep againe, and wakened as full of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary joyes, as formerly ſhee had been of terrors; rejoycing exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116556:10"/>and then told her Mother, <hi>What a wonderful comfortable dreame ſhee had been in, and how from an Angel ſhe was aſſured of her ſalvation; that now all her former feares ſhee ſaw were falſe, now ſhe would doubt no more, being aſſured to goe unto Heaven;</hi> and ſo prayed againe with her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Some houres after this ſhe fell aſleep againe for an houre and more (as her Mother told the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator) but at her awaking was now in a more fearfull caſe then ever,<note place="margin">The tempeſt begins roughly.</note> in a fearefull trembling and ſweat, ſhaking exceedingly and crying out, <hi>That now ſhee was a forelorne creature, being aſſuredly damned, without hope of mercy, without all remedy, confident that ſhee muſt needs goe unto hell; with ſhricks and loud Cryes, the bed ſhaking,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116556:11"/>yea, the whole chamber ſeeming to rock and reele:</hi> Which breeding to her Mother, much fear, amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and grief, in that it was now paſt her skill to faſten upon her daughter any thing which might allay, comfort, or quiet her diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſhee now was in. In which wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poſture ſhee ſtill continued, notwithſtanding all the comforts of perſwaſions vented either by her Mother or any others; all which were in vaine, there being joyned with her ſadneſſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, ſome out-rage now and then, abſtinence from meat as much as might be; ſtrange deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſpeeches, unruly carriage, far from her former naturall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution: ſometime ſlighting and laughing at all ſaid unto her, they now not daring to truſt her alone, but to have her watched continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116556:11"/>night and day by two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women by turns, moſt of the bolts and locks being taken off in the roomes, leſt Satan ſhould have circumvented them. Shee in the meane time all this while living in much diſcontent, againſt her will, but that ſhe was ſo watcht and tended, that ſhee could by no meanes hurt her ſelfe, never left alone, but over-awed with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers who were jealous of her ruine. In this Caſe ſhee with much adoe was brought to eat, but ſparingly, very muſing and ſilent; but when ſhe was by her Husband, Father or Mother, much urged to the contrary; who by their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity only prevailed much with her: now at length growing deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hopeleſſe, refuſing all meanes, ſlighting and ſcorning to ſpeake with any Miniſters, all who came
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116556:12"/>to her, ſhee ſhaking them off, as we ſee a great Maſtiffe to turne off many ſhall Curres; laughing at them, and ſending them away with much deriſion and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; which ſhee of purpoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to doe, ſo to diſcourage all of them, that they might have no minde to return again: So as ſhee wearied out all who came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, who left her as a creature hopeleſſe of recovery. In which ſad Poſture, now in her own eyes and moſt of others, hopeleſſe and helpleſſe, being the aſtoniſhment of Husband, Father, Mother, and of all her friends; wee will now for a while leave her unto her keepers, to ſhew in the next place, the ſecond thing propounded; <hi>How ſtrangely the Lord cauſed the Relater to bee a meanes to finde her out, bring one of a thouſand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116556:12"/>her, and what ſtrange entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhe gave him at his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming unto her,</hi> to declare unto her, both what her iniquity, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe was.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">How God cauſed to finde her out.</note>As by Gods good Providence the Relater was one day at dinner in <hi>Iſleworth,</hi> at the houſe of the Lady <hi>Scudamore,</hi> where the late worthy Miniſter Dr <hi>Burges</hi> the Elder then alſo was, whoſe help ſhee had rejected. Amongſt other diſcourſes there interpoſed this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of Mrs <hi>Drakes</hi> great diſtemper, pitifull ſtrange unuſuall Caſe, how deſperate it was, and what a great work of mercy it would bee to be a meanes any way to help her. It then being concluded by all, that if Mr <hi>Iohn Dod</hi> of <hi>Aſhby,</hi> could be entreated or won to take ſo much paines, under God he were the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit perſon, with his ſo milde,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116556:13"/>meek and mercifull ſpirit, do deale with hers, which was ſo out of tune and off hooks: upon whoſe prayers and paines, more good ſucceſſe might be expected, then any one they could then think of. This motion though for the time neglected, yet after a fortnight wrought ſo ſtrongly, day and night upon the Relater, that he could have no reſt until hee had moved the buſineſſe unto Mr <hi>Dod</hi> then in Town; who modeſtly put it off as a buſineſſe beyond his ſtrength and leiſure to wait upon, yet being contented to ſee her and ſpeak with her. Whereupon the Relater then wrote unto her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band (a ſtranger unto him) to this purpoſe; that hearing of the ſtrange Caſe and danger his wife now was in, out of mercy unto her, he had procured, the fitteſt man
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116556:13"/>known to come to ſee her, and do his beſt to help her according to his ability, one Mr <hi>Dod</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Cannons-Aſhby</hi> in <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonſhire.</hi> Hee then after enquiring of Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> found ſuch a generall good report of him, that he ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly came unto the Relaters chamber in the White-Friers, where Mr <hi>Dod</hi> at that time was, who acquainting himſelf with him, entreated his help and company to viſite his wife, and ſo took us both along with him unto his houſe.</p>
            <p>But it is ſtrange to heare what ſuttlety the Devill then uſed,<note place="margin">A ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Satan.</note> and uncouth entertainment he cauſed her then to give unto him: for, ſhee being in the dining roome above, having no knowledge of his comming (which was concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from her) yet as we came neare unto the door below, ſhe ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116556:14"/>flung up ſtaires unto the next chamber above, and ſhut her ſelfe in: Whereupon her Husband took the great iron forke in his hand, and run up after her, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to beat down the door, if ſhe would not open it. Who ſeeing him reſolute ſo to doe, at length opened the doore and let them in; her Husband then getting betwixt her and the door, they both kneeled, and Mr <hi>Dod</hi> (as his cuſtome in great matters was) kneeled and went to prayer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeaking of one word unto her: at which time ſhee ſtood and would not kneele, untill the latter end of the ſame, when ſhee alſo conformed her ſelfe, and kneeled with them. Prayer being done, Mr <hi>Dod</hi> ſaid nothing unto her, but in her hearing uttered ſome ſpeeches concerning her Caſe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116556:14"/>unto her Husband, tending unto her comfort and encouragement for her to make uſe off: and ſo did both before and at dinner, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting from her ſome ſpeeches to have given ſome pertinent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for further diſcourſe with her, which ſhee at that time omitting, he ſupplied with other ſeaſonable diſcourſes for her good, touching his experiences in the like kinde, of the Devils ſuttleties and the danger of keeping his councell, with the advantages accrewing unto him thereby; whereunto ſhee patiently attended. Dinner being done, he being asked in his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at her houſe (where hee now was perſwaded to lodge) what he thought of the buſineſſe? made this gratious hopefull Reply; <hi>very well, becauſe the Devill was afraid, run away, and durſt not ſtand to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116556:15"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Shee ſeemes to neglect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note>That night after ſhee was a bed, he was brought in by her husband to pray by her; but ſhee ſeem'd as though ſhee would not hear, hid her ſelfe over head and eares in the bed: notwithſtanding which he went on conſtantly in his determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto the end thereof. The next day at his comming, hee ſet in to ſpeak with her; at which time ſhee replyed nimbly and ſtrongly, uſing to purpoſe all, or much of the Devills rhethorike taught her againſt her ſelfe; yea, and alledged many Scriptures,<note place="margin">Strange.</note> which ſhee had never read, but only as tumbling and toſſing over the Bible (as her cuſtome was) to finde places againſt her ſelfe, ſhee had hit upon many; which by her nimbleneſſe and ſtrength of wit and Satans help, ſhee had learned to wreſt, and preſſe hard againſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116556:15"/>her ſelfe.<note place="margin">A ſad ſore and wofull conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the time.</note> But in all her diſcourſes with him, the upſhot of all ſtill was, <hi>That ſhee was a damned Reprobate, muſt needs goe unto Hell to live for ever; that her heart was harder then an Adamant or Anvile, that God had forſaken her, and given her over unto a reprobate ſenſe, her hard heart could not repent, and that in all her actions ſhee but heapt up wrath againſt the day of wrath to her further condemnation; and that in that ſhee could not grieve, nor be ſorrowfull for that wofull eſtate ſhee was now in, this ſhew the deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof; that it was in vaine, and too late for her to uſe any meanes: and therefore, that ſhee would uſe none, nor ever goe to Church againe. That it was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse, fruitleſſe and in vaine, for him or any body elſe to looſe their time or labor any more with her or her
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116556:16"/>occaſions, the Decree of her rejection and damnation being paſt and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable: And therefore, all her comfort and portion being in this life, ſhee was reſolved to ſpend the remainder of her time in all jollity and merriment, denying her ſelfe of no wordly comforts; and therefore, wiſhed him to let her alone, for it was impoſsible for him to doe her any good, nor ſhee would not either be ruled or adviſed by him;</hi> with a great deale of the like ſcurvie rotten ſtuffe, <hi>and that ſhee was quite deſtitute of all naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection unto Husband, Father, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Children, and every body elſe, having in briefe no love either to God or man; and therefore perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to leave her, not to pray for her, nor come any more at her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here was a ſad diſcourſe, with heavie accuſations againſt her ſelf,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116556:16"/>had all been true; but the Devill being a lyar, and the Father of lies, made her thus fiercely and unjuſtly accuſe and charge her ſelfe in ſuch rigor: for even then ſhee feared Hell fire, quaking ſometimes, and trembling at it, venting her ſelfe unto her friends in private, and weeping bitterly, ſhee uſed to ſay, <hi>O doe not yee pity me, who muſt goe to live in Hell torments for ever?</hi> Beſides,<note place="margin">A ſtrange hypocri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e unuſuall.</note> even then ſhee was piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and mercifull unto others, but in ſecret ſo hid and clokt with words and ſhewes of the contrary, that it was treaſon againſt her for any ſhe entruſted, to bewray any part or parcell of her goodneſſe; becauſe ſhee would gladly have beene thought paſt hope, and praying for, which made her ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to begge of every one not to pray for her, it being that the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116556:17"/>Devill aymed at, that ſhee might, paſt hope,<note place="margin">A new invention of Satan.</note> finally diſpaire. For, for two years together, by her good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will will ſhee would not bee prayd for, uſing many times at her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers uſuall time of Prayer to ſend ſuddenly for her, of purpoſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt her, who if ſhee came not preſently, as ſent for; when ſhee came, asking her pleaſure, ſhee uſed to reply, now I have nothing to ſay unto you, for you have been at your Matins. But to return to Mr <hi>Dods</hi> progreſſe with her; It was yet none at all, ſhe remained ſtill the ſame, ſeemed not to hear or regard his ſpeeches and words ſpoken; would laugh and jeſt at all he ſaid in deriſion: In her thoughts likening him unto <hi>Ananias,</hi> one whom at a play in the Black-Friers ſhee ſaw ſcoft at, for a holy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> and when he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116556:17"/>look pitifully upon her and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove her for ſuch ſtrange carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages and ſpeeches, telling her what a ſhamefull thing it was, ſo to laugh and jeſt at heavenly things; ſhee uſually Replyed, <hi>Why then, ſeeing you ſee what a wicked creature I am, why doe you trouble your ſelfe any more with me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divers faſts were kept for her in private,<note place="margin">Another of his ſubtile devices.</note> the next Chamber above hers, both then and divers times after, in midſt whereof the Devill ſo made her reſtleſſe, that ſhee would come up to the doore, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe them, of purpoſe, and make them believe that if the deſiſted not, ſhe would throw her ſelf down ſtaires headlong. Yea once ſhee being a bed, and he at prayer, ſhe to make him leave off, took a bed-ſtaffe, and threatned to knock him on the head, but did not. All theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116556:18"/>and many moe tricks the Devill u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſtill upon occaſion to ſerve his turne, changing his weapons, ſo as ſcarcely could it be known at what ward to finde him long: ſo to ſhew his malice, did he change his poſture and weapons.</p>
            <p>Now ſhee would toughly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute the buſineſſe,<note place="margin">She holds faſt her dolefull concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> but all to no purpoſe, ſhe retaining thoſe devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh concluſions faſtned in her ſtill. So that Mr <hi>Dod</hi> wearied out thus, having ſtaied a Moneth with her departed home, ſtayed away a Moneth and returned againe, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus three or foure times to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: yet found no amendement, but ſtill the ſame arguments ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintained over and over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine a hundred times together, without any good (in ſhew) effect upon her, who could not in two yeares time be won or perſwaded
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116556:18"/>to come to Church or Sacrament, or to uſe any meanes at all; but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her ſelfe as a deſperate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne creature, notwithſtanding which the over-coming thoughts and terrors of Hell did much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright her; ſo as gladly ſhe would have had a doore of hope opened unto her:<note place="margin">A nice prety ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that ſhe wiſht for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</note> For, a Kitchin-Maide ſhe kept, who had both wit and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory enough to do and retaine a meſſage; ſhee would uſually ſend unto divers Preachers with Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of enquiry touching her (concealing her name,) <hi>Whether ſuch and ſuch a creature, without Faith, Hope, love to God or man, hard-hearted, without naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, who had rejected all meanes, nor could perform any, or ſubmit unto the ſame, with many the like aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations</hi> (bad enough you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) <hi>yet might have any hope to go
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116556:19"/>to heaven?</hi> Who ſtill brought unto her ſuch returns tending to hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full encouragement: that ſuch like and much worſe (though as bad as <hi>Manaſſeth</hi>) might by the mercy of God be received into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, converted and ſaved, which privately did much allay her ſpirit; for no worſer returns of her ſecret meſſages were brought unto her from any ſhee had ſent unto.</p>
            <p>For all this,<note place="margin">A fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</note> yet did the Devill hold her cloſe unto his maine end of deſperation, to have made her ſelf away: For ſhe ſwallowed down many great pins, ſo to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch't her ſelfe; all which by Gods mercy without hurting paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through her: And being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Oranges (as naught for her) ſhee made ſhift by the foreſaid Maide to have forty brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, ſo to have ſped her ſelfe;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116556:19"/>but it ſo pleaſed God, that theſe proved excellent medicines unto her, purging away abundance of black ugly filthy matter, which made her to look much better. Shee uſed alſo now and then <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at meales, to ſhift a knife ſecretly in a napkin, and then to ſlip it up in then inſide of her arme; but being watched and taken therewith ſhee left off ſo doing, thus continuing, untill ſhee had in a manner weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out every body: for, <hi>the ſhorter the Devils reign was, he played the more tricks, making her by fits to be the more raging and troubleſome unto her ſelfe and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A ſtrange farewell.</note>Now as is ſaid, Mr <hi>Dod</hi> in a manner wearied out with her, as he was about to goe home for a while, and to take leave, ſhe gave unto him this rude farewell, <hi>To pray him to get him gone, to return
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116556:20"/>no more unto her, enquiring at him what warrant he had, being a holy religious man, who ſhould give good example unto others, to leave his Calling, Houſe and Family ſo long, and to come to her, where he was but an unwelcome Intruder, having no hope to doe her any good?</hi> Which ſpeech was ſo ſet on with ſuch an edge of vehemencie (ſpoken as it appeared againſt her will to prove him only) bred in him ſuch aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as reſolving to follow her counſell, hee made her this ſhort Reply, <hi>That this was but a bad requitall of all his paines and love unto her, to have no more thanks for his labour, but to be chid out of doores, that hee was very ſenſible of her reproofe and diſmiſsion, and therefore meant hereafter to ſtay at home, and look unto his own mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, not troubling her any more:</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116556:20"/>Which ſpeech it ſeemed touched her to the quick; for though to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage him and trie him, ſhe had made him ſuch an untoward ſpeech, yet was ſhee inwardly very ſorry for what was done: Only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departure, ſhee took him aſide, deſiring to ſpeak with him in private; when ſhee told him, that now ere his departure ſhee would deale freely with him, and ſhew the cauſe and ground of all her diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and trouble, and what juſt cauſe ſhee had thus to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, as hopeleſſe, enjoyning him ſilence.<note place="margin">A way opened for her cure.</note> And ſo in her own chamber, none but he being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſhe opened her whole heart ſincerely, ſo as hee perceived that ſhee had concealed nothing from him of all that was in her heart; which made (now that the Devils counſell was out and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116556:21"/>to conceive good hope of her recovery.</p>
            <p>For this quite marres, and is in danger to over throw all ſuch perſons,<note place="margin">Danger of concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Devils counſell.</note> whilſt the Devill ſo holds them in bondage, as to make them conceal his counſell all the while, having this advantage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as <hi>to make mountaines of mole-hils, and of mole-hils to make migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty mountains;</hi> never ſuffering them to come unto the knowledge of the quality and nature of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, whilſt the thing oppreſſing and ſeeming great unto them, is uſually little, and nothing at all in reſpect of that he makes it; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times but a lie, a deluſion, ſuch as the parties themſelves upon ſuch diſcoveries in relating become aſhamed of; As in ſome ſort it fell out with this good womans Caſe, which was nothing in a manner in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116556:21"/>regard of that the Devil urged and perſwaded her; it was, he proving a ſtrong lyer unto her, and his ſuggeſtion only a meare falſe illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as will hereafter appear. Then unto all that which ſhee had then vented unto him, he then made her only this generall Reply, <hi>That ſhe was much miſtaken and deluded in the quality, kinde and nature of her Caſe, that the Devill had thus far tormented her ſpirit with a ſtrong abuſe in corrupting her judgement; and encenſing her ſo unjuſtly againſt her ſelfe, ſetting her affections on fire, by his injected wild-fire temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. That he made no doubt of her recovery; but that now being acquainted with her Caſe and minde, hee would goe home and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with God what were fitteſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers for the ſame; returning ere long againe if God were ſo pleaſed:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116556:22"/>then to endeavor to ſatisfie and heal all her doubtings: In the meane time, untill then, enjoyning her chearefulneſſe, patience, moderation in all things before her Husband and Parents, and to attempt no more violence againſt her ſelfe; all which ſhee faithfully promiſed and kept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Still ſhee holds the maine concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>Hee being gone, in his abſence ſhee carried her ſelfe diſcreetly and modeſtly, not refuſing to ſpeak with any of thoſe Divines who in the interim came to viſit her; and would ſit and diſpute with them a long time together, but ſtill in the old bias, holding her ſtrong maine concluſions, the fabrick whereof appeared to be ſo ſtrongly rooted in her, that they ſeemed unremoveable, all who, as appeared, did no good unto her, ſave ſo much as they could to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116556:22"/>her from ſuch ſtiffe peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory concluſions againſt her ſelfe, and from prying into Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, preſuming to know thoſe things which God in this life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales not unto any, but reſerves as his own high prerogative, only to know what his decree is touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the everlaſting ſtate of the Creature to come: affirming that this knowledge which ſhe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to have thereof was falſe, and that this revelation, was only known in the ſanctified uſe of meanes, which ſhee ſo farre refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as ſhe could not be perſwaded to goe to Church by any, though they much urged her unto it: On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now ſhe would kneele and joyn in prayer with them, but by no meanes in ſinging of any Pſalme, which ſhee affirmed not to belong unto any in her Caſe, being now
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116556:23"/>very ſad and retired, and now and then in weeping fits, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in ſhewes of jollity and mirth, ſo by turnes it pleaſed her to out-face her preſent miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Patience, modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and milde dealing much prevails with ſuch.</note>But this as a Catholicon we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in dealing with her, that the more patient we were, to ſuffer her to complaine and bemoane her ſelfe, repeat one thing over a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times as ſhee uſed, over and over again, giving her good words, uſing much meekneſſe, affability and ſervice unto her, even in her moſt untoward croſſe carriages, this got much ground upon her ſpirit, and brought her to doe many things which no harſh croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe could poſſibly effect with her. And therefore this couſe was now taken, not to vex her any more, or urge her with perſwaſions to goe to Church, or to doe any thing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116556:23"/>ſo diſpleaſing unto her, but to goe along with her ſpirit, with patience abounding with love, mercy, good words and the like, untill ſhee were convinced in judgement, when they needed not to hale or pull her, <hi>Duties would then come off freely:</hi> For indeed, this is the undoing of many poore ſouls in the like, or any diſtempers, to chide, rate, and urge them to much; which is a croſſe way, diſpleaſing and unproſperous, yea, diſproportionable unto that courſe Chriſt takes (whom wee ſhould imitate) <hi>not to break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flax;</hi> and a croſſe way, <hi>To make judgement return unto victory:</hi> In which Caſe, <hi>Iacobs</hi> pace with his flocks, with ſuch, is the beſt and ſafeſt way to drive them gently; eſpecially thoſe who are with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116556:24"/>young, in whom Chriſt is now but abreeding and forming, <hi>that ſo he may</hi> (as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53) <hi>ſee of the travell of his ſoule, and be ſatisfied:</hi> And indeed, ſuch harſh ſpirits who are too quick with ſuch poor ſouls being too nimble with them before they know their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, are but <hi>like rude Surgions, or unskilfull Phyſitians, who venter to give phyſick before they know the ground of the diſeaſe;</hi> who many times in place of curing, doe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kill, or ſo much the more ulcer their wounds.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we have ſeen Satan malicious,<note place="margin">A change in her occaſions.</note> violent, ſubtile, various in his temptations, changing ſhapes, by all meanes ſtriving to have overthrown this good ſoule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> abuſe her judgement, affections, fancy, and beſt reaſon to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her ſelfe; notwithſtanding
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116556:24"/>all which, the Lord miraculouſly preſerved her, was with her in, and brought her through this fiery affliction, to wonder and admiration: Wherefore, if the Reader will have a little more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, he ſhall ſee how the Lord overthrew all thoſe ſtrong holds, which the enemy had by his wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire unreſiſted temptions, and fiery darts injected in this good creature; which being not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently caſt forth againe (as wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire ſhould be) thus enflamed her affections and endeavours againſt her ſelfe; as in part hath been and God willing ſhall be related.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Tempta∣tion. </seg>1</label> For firſt, he faſtned this temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon her, as his great maine Bulwork, <hi>That ſhe had ſinned that great unpardonable ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt;</hi> and therefore, that it was in vaine for her, either to uſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116556:25"/>any meanes for ſalvation, or hope for it; and therefore, that it were fruitleſſe and in vaine for her to heare the word, read, pray and the like; which hee wonderfull faſtly had radicated in her.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Tempta∣tion. </seg>2</label> Hereupon, hee inferred that <hi>by Gods Decree ſhee was a Reprobate, a caſt away, appointed for damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; being ſhee was ſuch a hard-hearted impenitent ſinner, not being able to repent:</hi> and therefore was a treaſurer up in all ſhee did of wrath againſt the day of wrath and the revelation of Gods juſt Judgements againſts her: and therefore, ſeeing that ſhee muſt eternally periſh, living for heaping up ſin only for aggravation of her puniſhments, therefore to make her ſelfe away, the ſooner the better: which temptation a long time ſtuck faſt, ſeeming unremovable.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:116556:25"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Tempta∣tion. </seg>3</label> From whence Satan made this third deduction (like a Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Logitian, begging the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) that <hi>therefore now it was in vaine to uſe any meanes at all; but ſeeing her portion was now only in this life, therefore to deny her ſelfe no manner of pleaſures or jollity and mirth, but to caſt off all theſe ſad and ſoure things of holy duties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, which were to no purpoſe, now that the irrevocable Decree was paſt, which was unchangeable:</hi> And therefore, if ſhee ſhould bee ſaved ſhee ſhould bee ſaved how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and that God would ſoften her heart, and give her grace to uſe the meanes: But that the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of her eſtate did ſhew (hee ſuggeſted) the contrary, that all her endeavors would prove in vaine; this ſtuck hard a long time.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116556:26"/>
            <p>Now againſt any of theſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bee faſtned upon her againſt them, which was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhook off again: But eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in that firſt mentioned of the <hi>Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhee kept cloſe the Devils coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, revealing the ſame at firſt unto none, but unto Mr <hi>Dod;</hi> though afterwards of her ſelfe three years after, being in a good humor, ſhee acquainted the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor herewith; and more alſo then he hath thought fit to vent abroad (as unneceſſary) giving him leave to publiſh and make known after her death ſo much of her Caſe as might in ſome ſuch miſery be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto others.</p>
            <p>After this Mr <hi>Dod</hi> at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time returned, having ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly pondered all her buſineſs, &amp; digeſted the ſame, and was joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116556:26"/>welcomed of her friends, though by her in a muddy ſtrange way (former tentations by that time, having againe growne ſomewhat ſtrong upon her) when yet hee in his uſuall mercifull way, cheared her up, encouraging her what poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he could. And ſo in ſome few dayes after fell flatly upon the buſineſſe, how to beat down and convince her erroneous opinions wherein ſhee was ſo ſetled, and wherein ſhee thought her ſelfe moſt ſecure in her owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unremoveably ſetled.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt diſcuſſed and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>The maine &amp; grand matter trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling her, and quite unhooking her off from all manner of duties (as hath been ſaid) was, <hi>That ſhe had ſinned that unpardonable ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, which ſhee firmly believed:</hi> Whereunto Maſter <hi>Dod</hi> thus replyed, directly croſſing all
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116556:27"/>her thoughts herein, in the <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> affirming that ſhe neither had ſinned this ſinne, nor was ever hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſo qualified, as to be guilty thereof; which ſeemed unto her very ſtrange to prove, but was eaſily done. For, he ſhewed unto her, our of <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. That thoſe who commit that ſin fight againſt their convinced enlighting, having taſted the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come, having alſo taſted of the heavenly gift, being made partakers of the holy Ghoſt; who in their practiſe crucifie to themſelves the Sonne of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame; and trample upon the blood of the Covenant, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly oppoſing the known truth, in a conſtant courſe remorſeleſſe unto the end: having lived &amp; thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven under powerfull means, which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116556:27"/>yet they ſlight, maliciouſly and purpoſly oppoſe and perſecute. But that ſhee being ſtill in her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural eſtate,<note place="margin">A ſtrong aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> by her own confeſſion being farre from this enlightning, never having taſted of this heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift, nor of the powers of the world to come, was never thus qualified, and ſo had never, neither could have committed this ſinne: ſo that her temptations and feares in this kinde were but meer deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons onely. And for that other ſort who committed this ſinne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the former inward illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and taſte, ſuch as were the <hi>Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> Julian <hi>the Apoſtate,</hi> and the like, who malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly perſecuted and blaſphemed Chriſt, notwithſtanding that by his Doctrine and Miracles they were convinced of his Diety; of this he ſhewed her, ſhee could not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116556:28"/>be guilty of, <hi>All ſhe could alleadge againſt her ſelfe, conſiſting only in a matter of thoughts, which could not without action and former qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation bee that ſinne, or within the compaſſe thereof:</hi> Which were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things wrapt up in that we call <hi>(tentatio Foeda)</hi> ſtrange injected thoughts of God, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.23. repreſenting him to the fancy in abominable ſimilitudes, likening him unto the vileſt and baſeſt things; which were only Satans wild fire tentations; for which ſeeing ſhee even then, and ſince, abominated them, being ſorry for them, Satan muſt anſwer for, <hi>they being hers no further then as ſhee entertained and allowed of them.</hi> And alſo, that theſe thoughts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought of and injected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the top and bottome of the hill whereupon her Fathers houſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116556:28"/>ſtood, never breaking forth into any ſpeech or action which ſhee was ſorry for, could not be any ſuch ſinne as ſhee imagined; and therfore prayed her to content her ſelfe and to reſt ſatisfied, and not ſuffer the Devill to delude and torment her any more in this kinde.</p>
            <p>All this diſcourſe ſhee heard willingly without replication un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he had finiſhed what he would ſay, when ſhee being very ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and convinced of the truth of what hee had delivered, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged her error, and Satans delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, promiſing no more to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any ſuch like thoughts of that ſinne,<note place="margin">A fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</note> 
               <hi>But withall ſhee told him, that it was no matter for this, though ſhee were free thereof, yet ſhe had other ſinnes enough to damne her, and was aſſuredly a Reprobate
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116556:29"/>and caſt away, being ſhee could not love God, nor any other creature, being devoid of all naturall affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and given over to a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe, ſo as ſhee was moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that the Decree of God againſt her was paſt, being that ſhee had no heart or power to performe any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duty, but was like a creature ſtarke dead, yea twice dead, good for nothing but for hell fire;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhee ſometimes would laugh and ſmile; but wee muſt conceive that even in the midſt of this laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the heart was ſad; for in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate not long after ſhee would have ſore fits of weeping.</p>
            <p>In vaine it was now to diſpute with her,<note place="margin">Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods Decree denyed unto any one.</note> or perſwade her in any thing untill her judgement was convinced &amp; rectified in that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Decree of God:</hi> For ſhee flung off all with ſeeming aſſurance
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116556:29"/>of her knowledge being ſure that the Decree of her reprobation was paſt, of her rejection whereof ſhe was ſure and certaine: Therefore, this being the next ſtrong hold to be battered down, he bent in the next place all his ſtrength this way, <hi>Denying unto her that it was poſsible either for the Devill, or any other creature to know the Decree of God, either for ſalvation or repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation;</hi> but that this revelation came in the uſe of meanes God bleſſing the ſame; for which cauſe all muſt uſe the meanes who would bee ſaved, not medling with the <hi>Decree of God,</hi> nor prying into his ſecrets; for which then was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that excellent Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.12. That what they were to performe and know, <hi>Was not in heaven, that we ſhould ſay, Who ſhall goe up for us to heaven, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:116556:30"/>bring it unto us, that we may heare it and doe it: Neither is it beyond the ſea, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, Who ſhall goe over the ſea for us? &amp;c. But the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart that thou mayeſt doe it.</hi> Further hee urged, that if thus much were certainly know by her, he ſhewed her, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>it muſt be by a Spirit of revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> demanding of her, what ſpirit had revealed thus much unto her? If the ſpirit of the Devill (as it could bee no other) then he was a liar and the father of lies, as Chriſt <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. ſpeaks, hee ſpeaking of his own and not from God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to believed. And as the for the Spirit of God (he ſhewed) who only ſearches knowes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales unto us the deep things of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. none but hee knowing the things of God, not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116556:30"/>any creature, <hi>This holy Spirit (he ſhewed her) had no ſuch office aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him of Chriſt in the word to be a ſpirit of diſcouragement to revealed reprobation, being the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter appointed to lead the Saints in all Truth, to reveale and tell things to come and teach us all things, Ioh.</hi> 14.26. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment. </seg>2</label> This were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt his nature, miſſion, and office, and the Decree of God, Thus to beat men off the uſe of meanes, diſcouraging them in the good way, who muſt wait and lie at the doore of mercy ſtill, untill the Lords good time and pleaſure were revealed and known in the uſe of meanes. And this alſo was preſſ'd unto her further, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment. </seg>3</label> what a horrible blaſphemy and impiety it were, either to honour the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſo farre, or aſſume unto her ſelfe by his meanes, the knowledge
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:116556:31"/>of things to come; this being that which was only proper unto <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> himſelfe, by his ſpirit to ſhew and reveale; adviſing her to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware in this kinde, not to encreaſe the wrath of God againſt her, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.7. &amp; 46.10. diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing himſelfe from Idols, and all their diſcoveries, is <hi>to know things that are come and a comming, declaring the end from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and from ancient times the things that were not yet done:</hi> From all which iſſued this deduction, that ſhee was infinitly abuſed in this ſtrange conception, and that the Devill or ſhee from him were not certaine of any things to come (unleſſe revealed by the Spirit of God) ſhee having from thence no ſuch revelation; that therefore ſhe was by Satan utterly cozened and abuſed in the matter of Gods
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:116556:31"/>
               <hi>Decree,</hi> and ſo was bound to uſe the meanes, truſt and wait upon God therein; ſhee being his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to let him do what he pleaſed with her, either in life or death.</p>
            <p>This ſtrong fiery dart thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed quenched, ſhee became alſo convinced in this point, that only God (not the Devill) could reveale his owne Counſels and Decrees; and therefore, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſhee might bee deceived in this her ſtrong confidence in that kinde: But ſtill retaining the third, <hi>That her indiſpoſition unto all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of goodneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Satan holds hard ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once got ground.</note> 
               <hi>proneneſſe unto all manner of evill, her naturall temper and compoſition of minde, not able to uſe any meanes, or take any paines for heaven, too evidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated that ſhee had no part or portion there, and therefore that ſhe had better leave off all then labor
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116556:32"/>in vaine:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Hereunto anſwer was made, That God though he had Decreed to ſave mankinde by the meanes of a Mediator, yet in his good wiſe Providence had ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the conveyance of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks) that <hi>he who made us without us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The uſe of meanes is ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preſſed upon her, to bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> 
               <hi>will not ſave us without us:</hi> &amp; therefore that all our life time we muſt be humble ſutors, labourers after, endeavourers and ſtrivers after that ſalvation which he hath appointed for us, uſing all thoſe meanes conſtantly, and not to lie ſtill in a ditch without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to riſe, and to cry Lord help us; ſuch a one hee told her did worthily periſh. It was further now alſo preſſ'd unto her, that God now after that miracle of all miracles, in the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Sonne to aſſume our fleſh and ſave us, now ordinarily
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:116556:32"/>wrought not the ſame miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, but by ordinary concurring meanes and endeavours revealed in the word; that as thoſe who in the Wilderneſſe were ſtung by the fiery Serpents, <hi>were not healed unleſſe they looked up unto the Brazen Serpent;</hi> no more any now could obtaine ſalvation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they believed in chriſt, its antitype: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment or motive. </seg>1</label> And that therefore, if ſhe uſed not the meanes, but rejected and wilfully withſtood the ſame, as there was no hope any way of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; ſo if ſhe uſed the meanes, there being hope, and many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes annexed to the ſame, there was good hope of her ſalvation; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment or motive. </seg>2</label> And <hi>put the caſe</hi> (which hee deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>that ſhe muſt needs periſh; yet much better it were to periſh in a way of obedience and duty full of hope all the way, and uſually ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:116556:33"/>whereunto were annexed many promiſes wherein the truth of god who cannot lie, but is faithfull in all his promiſes is engaged, then in a wilfull way of diſobedience.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment or motive. </seg>3</label> That all experiences ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world have ſhewed, that it never yet was in vaine, or unſucceſſefull, but alwayes advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous and proſperous to uſe the meanes, waite and depend upon God; yea, though it were as long and longer then the impotent man, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. lay at the <hi>poole of Betheſda,</hi> ere hee had help: And therefore ſeeing her caſe was now juſt like thoſe <hi>foure Leapers</hi> who ſate at the Gate of <hi>Samaria,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 4. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>4</label>
               <note>preſſed home.</note> Who being like to periſh in that great famine, reſolved, if, and ſince they muſt needs periſh, if they ſate ſtill there; but if they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured into the <hi>Campe of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116556:33"/>Aramites,</hi> they might peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be ſaved, (at the worſt but die) at their approach thither, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Amarites</hi> fled, they had choyce of the ſpoyle. So if ſhee uſed not the meanes, but deſpiſed them, ſhee muſt of neceſſity pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; but if uſed, ſhee might no queſtion be ſaved. And ſo to this effect were urged thoſe places, <hi>Micah.</hi> 2.7. <hi>O thou that art called by the name of the houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>is the Spirit of the Lord ſtraigthned? and thoſe his doings? doe not my words doe good to them that walk uprightly?</hi> and this, <hi>Seek yee the Lord, all yee meek of the earth, which have wrought his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſeek Righteouſneſſe and ſeek meekneſſe; It may bee yee ſhall bee hid in the day of the Lords anger, Zeph.</hi> 2.3. And ſo that of <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12. <hi>Therefore this will
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:116556:34"/>I doe unto thee, O Iſrael, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will doe theſe things unto thee, prepare thy ſelfe to meet thy God O Iſrael:</hi> even that God who is ſaid, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.8. to turn the ſhadow of death into the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; all which put her on ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto the matter of endevour, ſeeing as it is, <hi>Micah.</hi> 4.12. <hi>None know the thoughts of the Lord, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther underſtand they his counſell:</hi> ſo that their being a poſſibility for ought ſhee could know to uſe the meanes as ſhe was able; there was an abſolute neceſſity for her to ſubmit her ſelfe unto the meanes.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like things thus deliverd, did much amaze her ſpirit to have beene thus farre deluded and miſtaken in her own Caſe, and wherein ſhee was ſo ſetled, reſolute and confident; unto all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116556:34"/>which ſhee at length made this Reply,<note place="margin">Her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced anſwer.</note> 
               <hi>That now ſhe was convinced and did certainly believe, that none but God knew things that were to come; that ſhee had erred in judgement in ſo thinking of her ſelfe: That the deſperate Caſe and eſtate ſhee was in had cauſed her to make ſuch concluſions againſt her ſelfe: That now ſhee believed the Devill had no knowledge of Gods Decrees, concerning the everlaſting eſtate of the creature, no more then pleaſed God to reveale unto him: That ſhe was contented to do what ſhee could in uſing of the meanes, if ſhee might bee aſſured to reape any benefit thereby: But that the accidentall indiſpoſition both of her body and minde were ſuch, as ſhee in this Caſe could doe nothing to help her ſelfe, no more then a ſtark dead creature could; and therefore,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:116556:35"/>that God muſt doe all; in which Caſe, if hee were ſo pleaſed to give unto her ſtrength and grace to work, then ſhee would, otherwiſe ſhe could doe nothing:</hi> a ſore temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which even untill her laſt ſhe could hardly ſhake off.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Hereupon he Replyed, that God as was ſaid, wrought by meanes, and that ſhee was bound to read the Word di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, to pray, heare the ſame, meditate and conferre thereof: That this was Gods way and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed meanes, to make even ſuch dead creatures live, as ſhee preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her ſelfe to be as it is <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. <hi>That the time then was, and was a comming, when the dead ſhould heare the voyce of the Son of God, and thoſe who heard his voice ſhould live:</hi> Wherefore, ſeeing that their was ſuch a mervellous
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:116556:35"/>efficacy in hearing of the Word and uſe of meanes, <hi>(Wherein the power of the Spirit, did co-operate to make the ſame effectuall)</hi> There was an abſolute neceſſity to uſe the meanes for the attaining of ſalvation, or elſe one were thus guilty of their owne damnation in wilfull rejecting and refuſing of the meanes: Unto all which, her anſwer was, <note place="margin">Her fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.</note> 
               <hi>That ſhee had no power ſo to doe,</hi> but when that God <hi>would enable her, then ſhee would:</hi> Yet hee prayd her, to read the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Word and pray as ſhee could and the like, which ſhee refuſed, <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadging <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that ſhe could not pray; and for reading of the Word, to what purpoſe were that, ſo to read her own damnation, or to heare judgements and arraignments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her ſelfe; that ſhee was better as ſhee was; and therefore
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:116556:36"/>prayd him to urge her no more in this kinde, untill God were pleaſed to work ſomewhat in her, with abilities ſo to doe, which</hi> (if hee had a purpoſe to ſave her) <hi>hee would ſurely doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Shee is brought off and from the third grand tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>But for his paines and for his conviction of her judgement, rectifying of her from thoſe fore-mentioned errors ſhee gave him thanks, promiſing no more to torment her ſelfe with cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them; for ſhe was ſatisfied in the <hi>Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> in the matter of the <hi>Decree;</hi> and in Satan or her ignorance of any things to come, his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be none at all: <hi>But that for the preſent, here ſhee muſt reſt, no further ſhee could poſsibly goe, wiſhing him to ſhare himſelfe from being any more vexed with her untowardneſſe</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116556:36"/>
            <p>Hee much abaſhed at her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent diſtemper, and reſolute ſhew of ſtoutneſſe and ſtiffeneſſe of Spirit; yet was not diſcouraged, ſeeing he had got ſo much ground of Satan, as to beat her from her former ſtrong holds, hoping in time alſo to performe the reſt, which ſeemed a tough task to effect: becauſe the <hi>indiſpoſition and melancholy temper of her body was ſuch as hindered much the works, ſhee therewith being averſe unto Phyſick.</hi> Therefore,<note place="margin">Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to preſſe too much at once.</note> he reſolved for that time, to depart home and preſſe no more upon her at that time, but give her time to ruminate and think upon thoſe things deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, hoping to finde her in a better tune at his return, and ſo accordingly giving charge to watch her diligently, in a milde and loving way, after he had given
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:116556:37"/>her many and good Exhortations to uſe the means &amp; to have a good conceit of God, he departed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at this time hee would not tyre or overload her, or more new toyle out himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Satan is not idle, a new ſtorme ariſes.</note>A little after his departure ſhe began then to bee ſomewhat in the old poſture of frowardneſſe and diſtemper, uttering many times deſperate ſpeeches and hopeleſſe, ſtill refuſing all meanes; ſaying, that all were but in vaine: And was ſo farre gone this way, That <hi>the great ſnow, and all the diſaſtrous direfull events hapning abroad anywhere, ſhee ſaid were all long of her, and for her ſake, ſhe guilty of them, and that things would never bee better ſo long as ſhee were alive:</hi> For then indeed Santan taking advantage of her melancholy temper, wrought her
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:116556:37"/>much woe thereby, making her thus over-charge and accuſe her ſelfe, and endeavoring to have brought her back againe unto her former errors: So that now much adoe there was with her, to ſtay, ſupport, or allay that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall fierceneſſe, which now thoſe new diſtractions brought upon her; which bred much griefe unto her Husband, Parents and Friends, but was not ſo to be wondered at, that Satan ſhould cauſe unto her or them ſo much diſquietneſſe by his inceſſant new tentations, ſteering his time in Mr <hi>Dods</hi> abſence, to regaine his diſpoſſeſſed hold, or drive her unto finall deſperation.</p>
            <p>In, or neere this interim ſhee was viſited by divers worthy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters about the Town, amongſt whom was that famous worthy
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:116556:38"/>man, Dr <hi>uſher,</hi> ſince <hi>Primate of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a magzine of all knowledge and learning, a powerfull plaine Preacher, none like him in ſetting forth Chriſt in his high perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſurmounting excellencies, and in pointing the right ſtraight next way unto him; and withall as a very wiſe ſtout man, ſo the mildeſt humbleſt and meekeſt man alive, of his infinite reading, knowledge, and parts: This wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy man many times did viſite her, would intreat, perſwade, open Chriſt unto her, magnified the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Gods mercy that way ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto the ſonnes of men; ſhewing the freeneſſe of the gift of God this way, and that none were debarred, who did not wilfully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude themſelves, with much meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mildneſſe endeavoring to winne her ſpirit unto a reall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:116556:38"/>embracing of thoſe tenders of grace made unto her in the uſe of meanes; whom ſhee willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heard, delighted to hear ſpeak; but withall ſtill kept within the road of her old bias,<note place="margin">Her an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</note> 
               <hi>her inability to performe holy duties or endeavor that way; that all theſe were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things he ſpoke of touching Chriſt, for them unto whom they belonged, but ſhe had no ſhare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in for for ought ſhee knew ſhee ſaid:</hi> but yet uſed ſhee him alwayes with much love, reverence and reſpect, in whatſoever temper ſhee was in, endeavouring ſtill to give him all content and reſpect; and he being wiſe and judicious, ſeeing the temper of her ſpirit, a great work to bee wrought, the iſſue whereof time muſt ſhew, to bee effected by degrees, did not much preſſe upon her ſpirit, or much
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:116556:39"/>urge her unto any thing, being contented when he came to her to drop upon her many ſweet diſtilling ſhowers of precious ſpeeches; leaving them to work after he were gone.</p>
            <p>And now alſo about this time,<note place="margin">Her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with Mr Forbs.</note> came to viſite her another wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Miniſter, whom the Relater brought to ſee her and judge of her Caſe; a wiſe, acute, learned, diſcreet man, of great judgement and parts, one Mr <hi>Iohn Forbs,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Middleborrow</hi> for the Merchants. This man having firſt a great while viewed her and ſaid nothing, at length broke ſilence &amp; told her, that he had heard of her trouble and diſcouragements, and therefore had come to tender his ſervice unto her, to try if any thing were within the compaſſe of his power wherein hee were able to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:116556:39"/>ſerve here: Shee curteouſly gave him thanks, but withall told him <hi>that her Caſe and doome was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready determined and paſt, and therefore there was no good to bee done by any one unto her:</hi> Yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo an acute ſharp quick witty man, ſhee was pleaſed to have a ſtrong bout of diſcourſe with him alone, walking at her houſe in <hi>Eſher</hi> Gallery, where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving toughly diſputed with her a long time and no good to be done, but thwarted with many ſtrong uncouth objections and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſophiſtically applyed by her, beyond the skill or ſtrength of her own ſpirit or wit as hee judged, he confeſſed ſhe was too hard now on a ſudden for him. So at one bout having the better of her in a diſcourſe of <hi>Faith,</hi> he broke off laughing, with a jeſt, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:116556:40"/>her Husband near by an ſaid, Sir, now I can ſtay no longer, but I will ſtudy how to anſwer you Wives Arguments, and will now leave her in a good eſtate: <hi>(In faith, profeſsing infidelity,)</hi> who having taken his leave and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: The Relator enquired what his judgement was of her and her Caſe? Who made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That it was the ſtrangeſt that ever hee had ſeen, heard or read of<note place="margin">A ſtrange preſaging Cenſure.</note> 
               <hi>That the Lord had ſome ſtrange work to doe by her, but whether in mercy or judgement hee could not determine:</hi> no more hee would come to viſite her, nor could be drawn unto it.</p>
            <p>Upon this her late diſtemper and untowardneſſe, the good old man Mr <hi>Dod</hi> being againe ſent for and come, was notwithſtanding entertained by her in ſhew loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:116556:40"/>yet with a ſad louring coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance by and by accompanied therewith, as though hee had not been welcome; which he in his uſuall chearfull manner not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, uſing her with all meekneſſe and love, which he found gained much upon her ſpirit; after which having diſcourſed, &amp; two or three dayes prayed with her, and for her, ſhee began to mend, but yet could not be perſwaded to read, pray by her ſelfe, or goe to Chruch; wherefore hee thought it expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to leave urging thereof, untill her judgement were convinced therein: which was the next work to be done, a tough taske to effect, and which ſhee ſtrongly oppoſed and withſtood by one maine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument (being beaten off from all her other ſhifts) which was this out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:116556:41"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Whatſoever is not of Faith is ſinne; but ſhee did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, nor could doe any thing in faith, therefore all her actions muſt needs be ſinfull; ſo aggravating her condemnation, ſhee having ſinnes therefore enough to condemne her, would no more this way encreaſe their number already too many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> This Argument hee judged to be Sophiſticall, ſubtile, and a ſtrong fetch of the Devill, for his <hi>ultimum vale,</hi> and laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; whereunto hee after a little pauſe, thus Replyed, That <hi>he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the aſſumption,</hi> that ſhe could not doe anything in faith; for, <hi>the degrees of faith muſt be conſidered:</hi> There was a degree of initiation of babes in Chriſt, and of ſtrong men in Chriſt: <hi>That ſhe muſt now be conſidered of in the lower from of the ſchoole amongſt the babes in Chriſt,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:116556:41"/>needing milk not ſtrong meat</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though things were not done in a ſtrong, yet they might bee done in a weak and true faith, which might have a true and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table reward: So that there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the World many and large promiſes made unto the reading and hearing of the Word (ſome whereof wee then repeated) now for brevity omitted: That <hi>duties done in obedience unto the command of God, were then ſo done in faith, becauſe according to and with a reſpect unto the commandement;</hi> and muſt needs becauſe of the truth of God who cannot lie nor deny himſelfe, be rewarded. And put the caſe (which he then denyed) that ſhee muſt eternally periſh, yet <hi>God hath many out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mercies and bleſsings in ſtore,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:116556:42"/>wherewith to reward ſuch outward obedience, many times farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our ſlight performances, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from many temporall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, leſſening, delay, and mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, in number, weight, meaſure and continuance, remove-all of them and the like, in his beſt time:</hi> So that all things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the beſt for her were to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her ſelfe unto the will of God, lie down Saint-like at his feet: uſe the meanes, truſt, waite upon him, and then to let the Lord as (<hi>Ioab</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abner</hi>) doe that which ſeemeth beſt in his eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> And for that other cavill of the encreaſe of her ſins, in the matter of her endeavours; for this he told her, That <hi>all her good actions done, ſhould be upon record, &amp; all her ſins ſhould be forgiven and done away, ſo that this ſhould not hinder her obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent walking.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:116556:42"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Unto this ſhee objected her inability to performe any holy duty, and therefore ſeeing God in the up-ſhot of all his free pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes declares himſelfe thus (<hi>Yet for all theſe things, will I be ſought unto of the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael) <hi>ſhe not being able to aske or make obedient endeavour to wrap her ſelfe up within the promiſe, ſo as to have intereſt, or challenge the ſame, that therefore it were in vaine for her to uſe any meanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Reply hereunto was made, That true it was, that this was the ordinary roade of Providence in deſpenſing of ſalvation, to ſue and challenge the promiſes for our owne comfort, and to diſpence ſalvation in the uſe of meanes: <hi>Yet that God being a free agent to give and work at his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, had not ſo tyed himſelfe unto
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:116556:43"/>any methode ſo in his working, but that at his pleaſure he might deſpence therewith:</hi> And that therefore for her inability and weakneſſe, God could at his good time ſtrengthen her to his work, ſo in the meane time, that ſhee did her beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor according unto her ability, not being this way wanting; for where much weakneſſe was, yet God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times helpt and took in good part our weak performances, and that <hi>weakneſſe with truth and doing to our power went farre in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance:</hi> he loving us not for any thing in us, but freely for what he works in us; as that <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4. <hi>I will heale their back-ſlidings, I will love them freely, &amp;c.</hi> And that <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Vnto the Church of Philadelphia, Thou haſt a little ſtrength and haſt kept my word.</hi> So was ſhewed unto her that of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:116556:43"/>Diſciples, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.8. being weak ignorant men in many things touching ſalvation, for whom Chriſt yet pleads with his Father, <hi>They have kept my word,</hi> though formerly they were not able to beare thoſe things might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have been revealed unto them, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.12. Therefore from hence was much preſſed upon her the uſe of meanes howſoever unto her weak power and ſtrength, which God would encreaſe unto a greater growth, <hi>being that he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſtrength to the weak, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that have no ſtrength,</hi> Iſa. 40.29. Her Caſe was ſhewed her to be no worſe then that <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.4.5. of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in their own bloud, caſt forth in a miſerable condition, no eye pitying of them, any way to help them; whom yet God in his mercy
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:116556:44"/>pitied in that wofull condition, ſaying unto them, <hi>That even then they ſhould live, they ſhould live, when they were thus in their bloud, Ezek.</hi> 16.6. Therefore to hope well in the mercies of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not meaſuring the ſame by the ſcantling of her ſhallow conceits of God, in whoſe ſight all the ſinnes of the world are nothing, in compariſon of the infinite price payd of that blood of the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Covenant, and infinite value and merit of the ſame, which ſpeaks better things then the blood of <hi>Abel, Heb.</hi> 12.24. and whereby we have acceſſe with boldneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Throne of Grace, by a new and living way which hee hath conſecrated for us through the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ei<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, that is to ſay his fleſh.</p>
            <p>The ſtrength of theſe things thus enforced, ſo overcame her
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:116556:44"/>thus delivered, that herein ſhe was alſo convinced, that ſhee ought to uſe the meanes to her power, truſt and waite upon God for the iſſue, being contented of his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure whatſoever, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and promiſed, that now ſhe would goe to Church,<note place="margin">Shee is brought to goe to Church.</note> uſe the meanes and try what Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure were in time to doe with her; conceiving now ſome ſmall hope that poſſibly ſhee might bee ſaved in the uſe of meanes: and ſo was perſwaded to goe to Church; at her firſt going, being brought to heare Dr <hi>Gibſon;</hi> who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her comming, applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe covertly for her occaſions, yet not ſo, but ſhe ſuſpected that he had beene prompted, and had ſpoken things of purpoſe for her caſe (which ſhee murmured at) but was paſſed over; for indeed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:116556:45"/>the burthen wherewith ſhee had over-loaded her ſelfe was ſo great, that we durſt never adde any thing thereunto, but fed her with all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, ſhe being too apt to over-charge her ſelfe, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire upon any addition of fewell unto that fire which already was kindled in her: And ſo whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhee went to heare, notice was ſtill given, ſo to mannage their buſineſſe, that hee might know they had at that time a hearer thus qualified before them, whereby ſhee received no diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in hearing of the Word; but by the contrary matter of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, her ſpirit being ſtill jealous that all things were prompted for her ſake (hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring no more terrible things) as indeed they were.</p>
            <p>Yet in this interim, things being
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:116556:45"/>not yet well ſetled within her, not daring to truſt her alone, it was thought fit in the next place to fetch off her endeavours from her own deſtruction, which by Gods mercy was thus effected:<note place="margin">How ſhee was brought from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting againſt her ſelfe.</note> One day being in a very good humor, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and well pleaſed, Mr <hi>Dod</hi> prayd her that ſhe would reſolve him tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of one Queſtion, which hee would demand of her, which ſhe faithfully promiſed to doe. Then he demanded of her, <hi>That if now ſhee were condemned to be burnt, or hanged, drawn and tortured, to bee firſt rackt, ſcourged and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times whipt and tortured, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no ſhee would not eſteeme it to be a high favour and promotion, to be reprived and reſpited for ten or twenty yeares or thereabouts, to live longer?</hi> Which ſhee affirmed ſhee would take in this caſe for a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:116556:46"/>very high favour (not perceiving his ſcope and drift in the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;) Then ſaid he, tell me (taking her lovingly by the hand and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,) <hi>Why then did you all this while paſt make ſuch haſte to have poſted away unto Hell fire for ever, the torments and miſery whereof are many thouſand times in violence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all the poſsible torments of this world, ſeeing it is uncertaine whether ever you ſhall goe thither or not, but that God in the uſe of meanes will ſoften your heart and ſave you? But ſeeing the time</hi> (if ever) <hi>will be too ſoone whenſoever: therefore it were madneſſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame folly in you, to fall into that courſe which might precipitate and caſt you there preſently before the time; but to live forth natures courſe, trying what end the Lord will make:</hi> Shee being by her
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:116556:46"/>own confeſſion in ſome ſort catcht now as <hi>David</hi> was by <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, now perceiving the drift of this ſurprize, took him by the hand, and prayd him, <hi>That in that kinde no more jealouſie or ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might be had, for now ſhee was ſo by him convinced, that ſhee was reſolved to live ſo long as God would permit her, and that ſhee now was very ſenſible of his diſcourſe of Hell, and what ſmall reaſon ſhee had to make haſte thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus by Gods mercy brought her to ſubmit her ſelfe unto the meanes,<note place="margin">Shee is convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that ſhe ought &amp; might receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note> and hearing of Word, wherein faith and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are uſually conveyed and wrought; there wanting yet one thing, to bring her unto the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament (unto which ſhe was very averſe:) The next thing this good man went about, was how to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:116556:47"/>this, and convince her judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſhee ought, might and muſt participate herein, as well as in hearing of the Word: This was by her thought a very ſtrang thing to doe, that ſuch a one as ſhe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined her ſelfe to be, ſhould dare to Communicate. But hereof hee aſſured her the truth, from the equity and neceſſity of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God where <hi>all the Males in</hi> Iſrael <hi>were commanded to appeare three times a yeare before the Lord at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to eat of the Paſſeover; in which caſe whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever refuſed to come, or deſpiſed the ſame; hee was to bee cut off from his people:</hi> Whence he infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this concluſion, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our worthineſſe or unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in that caſe were, yet the command of God muſt be obeyed; all were bound to come and eat
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:116556:47"/>of the Paſſeover: And therefore that <hi>all within the Pales of the Church, ought to Communicate and receive the Sacrament howſoever qualified: In which caſe unworthy receiving ſhould not damne them, if once in all their life time they ſhould or did receive worthily:</hi> Shewing that in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> time, many then had received the <hi>Paſſeover</hi> unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, for whom notwithſtanding hee prayed the good Lord to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, though they had not eaten according unto the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſanctuary. Beſides this he ſhewed her, <hi>That the Sacrament was not a comforting, ſtrengthning, building up Ordinance onely, but alſo a converting and healing power being therein for help of the ſick and diſeaſed, a reviving quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Ordinance alſo; ſo as all ought to participate of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:116556:48"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Hereunto ſhe objected that out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receivers did eat and drink their own damnation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe durſt not adventure any more to aggravate her condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and puniſhments.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Unto this he Replyed, That ſhe was miſtaken in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the words, <hi>for the word</hi> Damnation <hi>muſt not there be taken in the terrible ſenſe,</hi> the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall not carrying it ſo, but thus, <hi>(ſuch eat Iugdement) unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> viz. <hi>temporall puniſhments:</hi> which the enſuing verſe 30. cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the ſame thus, <hi>For this cauſe many are weak and ſickly among you, and many ſleep, &amp;c.</hi> Which ſhewes the meaning onely is, that ſuch endure ſometimes temporall puniſhments; who yet may bee ſaved and goe to Heaven. So that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:116556:48"/>ſtill the generall holds in equity, as in and under the Law; that Gods Ordinance in the Sacrament is not to bee neglected of us for our unſufficiency and unfitneſſe for the ſame, no more then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law during the Paſſeover; becauſe, <hi>it may be a meanes to fit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Let the ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous note this well.</note> 
               <hi>heale, cure, ſtrengthen, revive, quicken and enable us to be worthy Receivers: For we come not to bring vertue unto the Sacrament, but to receive vertue, life, ſtrength and quickning from thence:</hi> And that howſoever in this caſe we be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, it were beſt to be obedient and uſe the meanes, all which with much more the Relator remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers not, was ſet on with more excellent illuſtrations, exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and pithy remonſtrances: which diſcourſe being finiſhed ſhe became in this alſo convinced in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:116556:49"/>judgement, that ſhee promiſed him thus farre to ſubmit herſelfe yet further unto the meanes, that ſhee would now alſo goe unto the Sacrament: <hi>Onely in this Caſe ſhe begg'd exemption not to be urged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee could not neither was able by her ſelfe to performe any private duties of prayer, or read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word conſtantly:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, becauſe they would not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver drive her, put her beyond her ſtrength, or moleſt her ſpirit, they ſpared to urge her, contented with what they could with gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and entreaty perſwade her unto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A very ſtrange experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note>Yet it is moſt ſtrange to heare, how the Lord dealt with her in one thing, wherein ſhe delighted, and was hardly broken off, <hi>viz. Shee had a cuſtome in tumbling over of the Bible, to put her finger
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:116556:49"/>ſuddenly upon ſome one verſe as it hit; ſaying, now whatſoever my finger is upon, is juſt my Caſe, whatſoever it bee, and my doome:</hi> But ſo the Lord directed all her fingers ſo put, that looking upon the verſe, ſtill it was found en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging and comfortable, not diſcouraging: whereupon being much prayed and entreated, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hitherto ſhee had found all places to ſpeak for her, that ſhee would deſiſt, and not any more thus tempt God; who prayd that ſhee might doe but once more ſo (it being in the preſence of many) promiſing faithfully that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that one time, ſhe would never do ſo any more, to attempt any ſuch tryall: Whereupon at length all adventured to ſuffer her once more to ſee what Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would prove in ſo ſtrange
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:116556:50"/>a Caſe. But withall if ſome croſſe place came, they prayed her not to bee diſcouraged; whereupon ſhee ſuddenly opened the Book, about the middle thereof, in the Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and without looking or reading a word, or knowing what ſhee did, ſhe put her finger upon that excellent verſ. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.27. <hi>Why ſayeſt thou O</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ſpeakeſt O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>my way is hid from the Lord? haſt thou not known, haſt thou not heard that the everlaſting God the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the ends of the Earth, faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, neither is weary; there is no ſearching of his underſtanding: hee giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth ſtrength; even the youths ſhall faint and be weary, and the young men ſhall utterly fall; But they that wait upon the Lord, ſhall
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:116556:50"/>renew their ſtrength, they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, and they ſhall walk and not faint:</hi> Which place being conſidered of and read, ſo croſſing her hopes and expectation, made her being much abaſhed to bluſh. For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhee was reproved for her croſſe conceits of God touching her, as neglected of the Almighty; and for all her weakneſſe and imperfections was ſhewed, that God could help all, who with a word made heaven and earth, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling her to doe all duties at his good pleaſure; being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with encouraged to wait and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon God in the uſe of meanes by ſuch an excellent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: And ſo was therewith ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how good God was unto her, every way ſhewing love, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding her untowardneſſe, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:116556:51"/>tempting of him by ſuch ſignes: At which, not knowing what to ſay, ſhee flung off poorely, ſaying, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> this was promiſed to <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> It was nothing unto her and her Caſe: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Whereunto anſwer was made out of that place, Rom. 15. <hi>Whatſoever was written before hand, was written for our learning, that wee through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope;</hi> and ſo was thereby vanquiſhed in judgement, that ſhe promiſed now to be ſatisfied, and never any more to make any ſuch tryall, but to offer her ſelfe unto the uſe of meanes, and to wait the Lords leiſure what hee pleaſed to doe with her: Yet ſtill alleadging the impotency in her, that ſhe was able to doe nothing herein to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this great work, but that God muſt doe all, when being
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:116556:51"/>enabled, ſhee would doe that whereunto ſhe ſhould be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Shee is perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to joyne in ſinging of ſome ſort of Pſalms.</note>Yet wanted there one thing more, to gether to joyn in ſinging of Pſalmes, which with much adoe ſhee was brought unto, <hi>alleadging that her Caſe admitted of no ſuch melody, neither had ſhee cauſe to ſing, but to mourn all her life time:</hi> Yet being told that it was a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſing prayſes unto God, for all his mervellous mercies, power and goodneſſe, as well as to joyn in hearing of the Word; and that <hi>thanksgiving being the everlaſting work of Heaven in continuall pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, was a work could not be too ſoone begun upon earth;</hi> and that the Pſalmes being of divers compoſitions and poſtures; of thankſgiving, petition, gratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, complaint, and deprecation,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:116556:52"/>ſhee might joyne in ſome, many of which might fit her Caſe; ſhee was contented to joyn in Pſalmes of complaint, petition, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deprecation, but in no other of any acknowledgement of any mercy received: For ſaid ſhe, <hi>If I be onely reſerved as a ſtalled Oxe unto the ſlaughter, what cauſe have I to give thanks; and if I be not to goe to Heaven, what have I to doe with the work of Heaven before the time, or having ſome work wrought in me, whereby I may be aſſured of my intereſt therein?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why ſhee would have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a powerful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</note>About this time willingly ſhee would have live under ſome powerful Miniſtry, hoping, that thereby ſome ſuch work might be wrought upon her, as might ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble her to performe duties; and for this cauſe ſecretly made the Relator goe into <hi>Eſſex</hi> to try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:116556:52"/>or not that worthy powerfull late thundering Preacher, Mr <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> of <hi>Dedham,</hi> would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained her at his houſe, who willingly granted the ſame: But when the buſineſſe was moved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Father and Mother, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they nor her Husband would conſent unto the ſame, though Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> and Mr <hi>Culver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> both affected to have gone with her, ſo too indulgent were they over her; which refuſall much unhookt her ſpirit, and had almoſt put her in her former Caſe againe, ſo much did it afflict her; but not remedy,<note place="margin">An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erience of her ſp<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> her.</note> at length ſhee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed her ſelfe unto neceſſity.</p>
            <p>I should much tranſgreſſe, and wrong this diſcourſe of Gods mercies into this good creature, if I ſhould omit any paſſage of Satans ſubtelties and attempts
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:116556:53"/>againſt her, how farre they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed; for ſo, <hi>the Power and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God unto her in ſaving her at length, will ſo much the more evidently appeare to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> Therefore this enſuing paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I relate, as the furtheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Satans malice: One day as ſhee was walking in her garden at <hi>Waltham</hi> upon <hi>Thames</hi> with the Relator and another friend (for <hi>Eſher that place where her trouble firſt began, ſhee never after could endure</hi>) ſuddenly ſhee ſtopt and fixed her eyes faſt upon the ground, ſtaring upon it with ſtrange wilde looks, for halfe a quater of an hour, from which we could hardly divert her, but at laſt did, though ſhee ſeemed much troubled to be interrupted; and then (as her cuſtome was when the waters of her ſpirits and thoughts
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:116556:53"/>were become muddy) ſhe began to ſeem to caſt off all means again; ſaying, <hi>That her heart was ſo heard, as it could never bee ſoftned; this was by thoſe with her then much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and denyed as faſt as ſhe affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſame,</hi> enforcing that God who with a Word made Heaven and Earth could ſoften it; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſhee in anger replyed, <hi>(why then God cannot ſoften my heart)</hi> at hearing of this blaſphemous ſpeech, ſpoken in the heigth of temptation, the Relator without ſpeaking one word unto her ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly left her; <hi>for ſuch ſpeeches were not to be born with, countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, or diſputed with, but to be caſt off, with deteſtation and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for <hi>(contra principiis non eſt diſputandum)</hi> they ſay: A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while after, ſhee being then ready to ride abroad and goe to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:116556:54"/>her houſe at <hi>Eſher</hi> to take the aire, going to take horſe, ſhee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the Relator, whether hee would not ride abroad with her, whereunto hee replyed, <hi>No, he durſt not goe in her company, who did ſo lately blaſpheme, for feare the ground would open and ſwallow them up; but that ſeeing under the Law the blaſpemer was to die the death; that he would go to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and complaine of her, beare witneſſe againſt her, and provide faggots to burn her;</hi> wherewith we both parted in ſeeming diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. She being gone, the Relator ere his way-going, went to her waiting-woman, and left his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance unto her, which when her woman, at her return told her; ſhee would not believe that hee had ſo done, but asked her Maide, what farwell didſt thou think hee
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:116556:54"/>gave me, <hi>That he would goe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of me, and provide faggots to burne me:</hi> To which her Maide anſwered, <hi>Then Miſtriſſe, you have ſpoken ſome ſtrange untoward things;</hi> I think I did ſo, ſaid ſhee: In this interim the Relator ſent and wrote very kindly to her in his abſence, and after a Moneths time returned againe unto her; when,<note place="margin">Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> 
               <hi>ſhee prayed him to ſtay no more ſo long away, gave him thanks for his harſh uſage of her; ſaying, ſhee had deſerved worſe, and would never ſo doe any more; Telling al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that then when formerly ſhe had ſtood ſtaring on the ground, ſhe was then aſſaulted with fierce and ſtrong temptations; all the while a brick-making for the Devill; and prayd him when he ſaw her do ſo any more, to put her out of that poſture, and not to ſpare her, how angry ſoever
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:116556:55"/>ſhee ſhould for the time bee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as ſhee was in a ſeeming good tune and poſture of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to uſe the meanes,<note place="margin">A new ſtorme.</note> in tumbling over the Bible, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred with that terrible place, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> enferred upon the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>That the ground which was often watered, and brings forth nothing but briers and thorns, was neare unto cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and burning, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Which place for a few dayes put her quite off hooks againe, affirming that ſhee was juſt ſo, a creature that brought forth nothing but briers and thorns, though ſhe had been often watered from heaven in the uſe of means, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſhe was neere unto cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and burning.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Firſt, This was deneyd unto her, that ſhee had ever lived under
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:116556:55"/>any ſuch powerful Miniſtry, as to have been often thus watered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, That ſhee neither hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto had beene ſo bad, as to bring forth nothing but briers and thorns, having to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge brought forth and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced much good fruit of her hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in times paſt, though now ſhee were for a ſeaſon over-cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with temptations, ſo, as ſhee could not diſcerne of her own eſtate, nor was apt to judge thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, That this place being enforced as a reaſon of the ſinne againſt <hi>the Holy Ghoſt, againſt their enlightning; which by her own confeſsion, was a pitch above her, that hitherto ſhee never had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto;</hi> therefore ſhe needed not to make any ſuch rigid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, or conſtruction of the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:116556:56"/>place againſt her ſelfe; wherewith, and the like milde ſpeeches unto her to this effect, ſhee was at length pacified as before.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney paſt recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>Good Reader be not weary, I will now ſuddenly make way unto a concluſion, for much of our work, and the greateſt part is done and hardeſt to compaſſe; Lo now, we have brought this good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> woman thus farre: <hi>To aske the way (in ſome ſort like one of</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remies <hi>Converts) to Zion with her</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>face thitherwards.</hi> She is brought out of the houſe of bondage, from he brick-making ſlavery, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> purſues as it were ſtill after her, but hath not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken her, ſhee is driven to flie and wander up and downe the wilderneſſe, now backwards now forwards, as the Church in the wilderneſſe was, ere ſhe can arrive
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:116556:56"/>at her heavenly <hi>Canaan;</hi> and I hope wee ſhall ere long ſee her <hi>Iordan</hi> ſtand up, and give her a faire paſſage in thither, though ſhee hath beene well buffeted by the way.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Shee hath been now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, not to have ſinned that ſin againſt <hi>the Holy Ghoſt</hi> (as Satan perſwaded her) being in this ſettled.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Shee hath been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in that grand buſineſſe of the <hi>Decree of God,</hi> not to meddle therewith, and that no Creature, Devill, Man or Angel, ſave God himſelfe had any knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, In the matter of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor, ſhe hath been convinced, <hi>that ſhee ought and muſt ſet her ſelfe in what poſsibly ſhee could, to uſe the meanes,</hi> wait therein, and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:116556:57"/>to truſt God with the iſſue of all.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Shee hath been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to live as long as poſsibly ſhee could,</hi> not to be a means of her own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Shee hath been perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>of the lawfulneſſe and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of her communicating,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all her ſeeming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſſe, and indiſpoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, Shee hath been brought from that courſe <hi>in tempting God by putting her finger ſuddenly upon places of Scripture,</hi> to try her ſtare, all which fell out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto her expectation, good ſtill.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, How and <hi>on what conditions ſhee was brought to joyne in ſinging of Pſalmes:</hi> all which being paſt, one would think, that now there had not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:116556:57"/>been much adoe, but to have had a quick end of her troubles, and ſufferings.</p>
            <p>But the Lord wonderfull in working, and excellent infinitely in counſell and wiſdome, had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſo appointed the ſame, that ſhee ſhould yet a few years longer be ſtorm beaten and ſick, and wander as it were in a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, ere ſhee arrived at her heavenly <hi>Canaan:</hi> And therefore out of her habituall impotencie ſeeing ſhee was ſo ſtiffe and ſlow to work out her own ſalvation or take paines for it, <hi>Shee had at length her deſire, though hee made it coſt her deare ere hee at length revealed himſelf unto her:</hi> And therefore heareat ſhee ſtuck ſtill even to the laſt, expecting what extraodinary work God would work in her, to enable her to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:116556:58"/>take paines for her ſalvation: <hi>A ſtrange temptation, which all her life time could hardly ever bee quite removed: Untill God in a ſtrange and unuſuall manner, for matter of feeling revealed himſelfe unto her in ſuch a meaſure, as mortality was incapable of, to the over-comming of her ſpirits</hi> (who lived not long after) <hi>to be in its place related.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time that famous worthy man of God, Mr <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> ſome time Miniſter of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denborrow,</hi> then in priſon amongſt the wilde <hi>Iriſh,</hi> for not preaching or aſſenting unto the truth of the Earle of <hi>Gowries</hi> Treaſon, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Relator the trouble and true ſtate of this Gentlewomans Caſe, with the progreſſe thereof, and how ſhee had been brought to reveale the Devils counſell,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:116556:58"/>wrote a letter unto the Relator touching his cenſure of her Caſe, and hopefull iſſue thereof: who being for afflicted conſciences one of ten thouſand (he himſelfe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene for twenty yeares in terrors of conſcience, ere he was forced to ſettle unto the Miniſtry) gave a judicious propheticall cenſure of the event of her caſe, as in ſome ſort it fell out (too long here to inſert) but in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with this upſhot: That now ſhee had bewrayed ſo freely the Devils counſell, hee knew that all would ſhortly bee well are long, and that her trouble would have to admiration a ſtrange event; and that for her finall eſtate, he thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God, he made no more doubt thereof then of his own, which he aſſured himſelfe of, becauſe God had given him ſo large a heart to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:116556:59"/>continue inſtant for her in prayer with a great deale of comfort; concluding his letter with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall ſpeech turned in behalfe of the Gentlewoman towards Satan, worthy to be written in letters of gold, which being ſo rare and unuſuall in the Preſſe ſpeeches of this nature, I have therefore adventured here to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <head>A Speech to Satan.</head>
                        <p>O Enemy Satan, although thy enmity for the preſent be troubleſome unto this patient, yet I thank my God through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that thou art an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my unto her; and that he hath put her in his Camp to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. When I conſider how in Paradice the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:116556:59"/>irreconciliable enmity betwixt thee and the bleſſed ſeed, I account her happy in that thou art her enemy, and that ſtrength is given her to fight againſt thee, for hereby I perceive that ſhee is none of thine, but ſtands on that ſide whereof Chriſt is the Captaine, and all the Saints are Souldiers; where the victory undoubtedly muſt bee both ſure and certaine on her ſide. O deceitfull Serpent! If we finde ſuch terrors and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of thy fury for theſe ſmaller ſinnes of frailty which we fooliſhly by thy enticement com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; what ſhould we have found if wee had followed thee, in the reſt of thy deadly aſſiduall and unmeaſurable fiery injected temptations? from the which the Lords preventing and reſtraining
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:116556:60"/>mercy hath kept us. I have often by experience heard that thou art a faithleſſe traytor; becauſe thou tempteſt a man to ſinne, and for the ſelfe-ſame ſinne which by thy inſtigation we commit, thou art the firſt accuſer, and the laſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter. The Lord encreaſe our faith, and confirme his good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in our hearts, that we never hearken any more to thy lying words, nor ſuffer our ſoules to be circumvented by thee and thy deceitfull ſnares. And as for the work of her ſalvation, ſince it is a work which our God will work in ſpite of thee; wherefore ſhould ſhee or wee any more regard thy lying teſtimony? Thou didſt moſt malitiouſly put the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto our Saviour, whether or no he were the Son of God? And then what marvell is it that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:116556:60"/>thou dareſt ſay unto his children that they are none of his? Is there any ſuch undoubted truth that thou dareſt not deny? or any falſhood which thou dareſt not make good and juſtifie? Why therefore ſhould we enter in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting with thee? for, her ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſiſts not either in thy queſtioning, or in her diſputing againſt it; but upon the Lords unchangeable Decree of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If thou ſhouldeſt ſpeak for her, and plead her cauſe, ſhe were ſo much the worſe, and nothing the better; and now that thou pleadſt againſt her, ſhe is nothing the worſe. I love no teſtimony which proceeds from thee. When thou confeſſedſt that Jeſus was the Son of God, he rebuked thee, and would none of thy teſtimony; and when thou cryedſt out that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:116556:61"/>
                           <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas</hi> were the ſervants of the moſt High God, although thou ſpakeſt the truth, yet they would not accept of thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. So although thou wouldeſt affirme that ſhe were the child of God, were ſhe any thing the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? no, but ſo much the worſe; thou canſt vent no truth but with an intent to deceive: Therefore keep thy teſtimomie to thy ſelfe, ſpeak what thou wilt, thou art ever like thy ſelfe, a liar; curſed art thou, and curſed ſhalt thou be, with all thy Confederates, and curſed are they that are in friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with thee: So in concluſion, thy purſuite of her, and her ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hitherto from thy power, ſhewes mee that ſhee is none of thine.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The Lord powre in his comfort and grace in her weak heart, that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:116556:61"/>ſhee may finde and feele the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the things we write of, and from her feeling to give God the prayſe of his glory, and of her victory, which I am ſure to be moſt certaine in Gods good time, and that her ſalvation is as ſure as mine own, I prayſe God.</p>
            <p>By this time three whole years having paſt, ſince Mr <hi>Dod</hi> began with her, having endured ſo many hot skirmiſhes with Satan, made ſo many long journeys, being toyld out in body and ſpirit, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous now to reſt awhile, having fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitated his tough task, and fitted it for ſome other to finiſh and build her up further, hee having in all things convicted her judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that God who does all things well, and makes all things <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. work together for good unto his children; who when
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:116556:62"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was old, appointed the young man <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in his place; and who when <hi>Manna</hi> failed, brought the people into <hi>Canaan</hi> flowing with milke and honey, did now alſo out of his good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence appoint a fit man to ſucceed as a helper in Mr <hi>Dods</hi> place, meet for that poſture of ſtrength ſhee was now in, <hi>In a ſtrange objecting, diſputing way, followed by Satans temptations, and prompted with ſtrong objections againſt her ſelfe:</hi> So that now her great want was of an able man to be continually with her, to diſpute conſtantly with all her temptations and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, able to anſwer and cruſh all.</p>
            <p>This and ſuch a Helper did God in his infinite mercy in the next place provide for her.<note place="margin">Another fit help ſucceeds to M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Dad.</note> For it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God in his wiſe providence, ſo
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:116556:62"/>to order the matter, that her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Cure at <hi>Eſher</hi> being a <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native,</hi> and not a <hi>Preſentative en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downment</hi> was voyde and to bee diſpoſed of: In which interim, notice was given unto him of one Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> then at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> now in <hi>New-England:</hi> A great Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, an acute Diſputant, a ſtrong learned, a wiſe modeſt man, every way rarely qualified; who being a Non-conformitan in judgement, not willing to trouble himſelfe with <hi>Preſentative</hi> Livings, was contented and perſwaded by Mr <hi>Dod</hi> to accept of that poore Living of 40 l. <hi>per annum,</hi> Mr <hi>Drake</hi> her Husband being a worthy wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved Gentleman, and able to procure his liberty, and retaine him ſtill in the ſame: This worthy man accepted of the Place, having withall, his dyet and lodging at
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:116556:63"/>
               <hi>Eſher</hi> Mr <hi>Drakes</hi> houſe; and ſo by this meanes, as to free Mr <hi>Dod</hi> from his toile and trouble, ſo to be at all aſſayes ready to mannage and work her ſpirit, encounter all her objections, eſpie all Satans windings and turnings, and catch her at all non-plus advantages, being acute, quick, nimble-witted, well skild in knowing and opening of the Scriptures; withall a good Logitian, a ſtrong Diſputant, as he could well doe. And ſo the good old man as occaſion ſerved, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing unto her, after divers ſad and ſerious diſcourſes with her, wherein ſhee covenanted to obſerve all promiſes paſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her former reſolutions in thoſe things wherin in judgement ſhe was convinced, he was for that time lovingly diſmiſſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded largely by her Parents.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:116556:63"/>
            <p>This man Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> being a good acute, ſmart Preacher when he liſted, beſides that information Mr <hi>Dod</hi> had given him, was ſo wiſe, firſt to trie her ſpirit, to finde her diſpoſition, uſing her with much mildneſſe &amp; love, ere he would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to meddle with her ſpirit, chuſing rather that way made from her might uſher the way unto his diſcourſe, then that at firſt hee ſhould enforce any thing upon her: Which was not long in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence; for now having a fit perſon to rough hew her (as it were) whom ſhee could neither weary out nor over-come in Argument, but was able to diſcerne and catch Satan in all his Sophiſmes, there every way fell out ſtrong diſputes betwixt them: But all within the compaſſe of thoſe former things wherein Mr <hi>Dod</hi> before had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:116556:64"/>her: Satan delighting ſtill to raſe new uprores in her, and (as his cuſtome is) <hi>not to ſuffer us to be at peace though we be out of danger:</hi> Such now were his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes anew, to winde up his old bottomes, and to renew diſputes, even in thoſe things ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of. For Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> being newly come from the Univerſity had a new anſwering methode (though the ſame things) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhee was mervellouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, and being very covetous of knowledge, was pleaſed with new diſputes and objections to faſten further upon her ſelfe thoſe forementioned things; ſtill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and further ſifting into the ſame old Truths whereof ſhee was well perſwaded (and as is ſaid) convinced.</p>
            <p>Yet could not he ſo evenly hold
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:116556:64"/>the ballance in mannaging of her ſpirit, but that now and then ſhee would flie out,<note place="margin">By de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſhe is ſometimes off hooks ſtill.</note> in many diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>wiſhing to leave off all, for ſhee now ſaw that there was no remedy, the meanes did not work nor prove effectuall unto her: To what purpoſe ſhould ſhee any more labour in vaine?</hi> But eſpecially towards the Sacrament, then uſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſhee would be off hooks, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not comming, or unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if ſhee did: Upon whom this place for her waiting and depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God was ſtrongly urged, <hi>Hab. 3. ult.</hi> That the viſion of Gods deliverances, was for an appointed time, therefore to wait; for though it tarried, yet it ſhould come and not tarry; and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8. <hi>I will wait upon the Lord, who hath hid his face from the houſe of</hi> Jacob; <hi>and I will look for
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:116556:65"/>him:</hi> affirming unto her that theſe and the like hard travels, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident unto Gods beſt beloved people, to have many, hard and long trialls, and yet at length glorious deliverances, as was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged from that place, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. <hi>You only have I known of all the Nations of the earth; therefore I will puniſh you for your iniquities:</hi> (which God may doe forgiving the ſinne, <hi>though bee take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of their inventions:</hi>) And that <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. what ſonne is there whom the Father chaſteneth not? If therefore yee bee without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection (whereof all are partakers) then are yee baſtards and not ſonnes. Which with the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations from the word cloſely urged, brought down her ſpirit to mildneſſe and meekneſſe: For though her indiſpoſition and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:116556:65"/>temptations, made her many times contrary unto her naturall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition harſh and untoward, with the habite ſhee had accrewed in time to be croſſe, and try thoſe ſoundly ſhee converſed with; <hi>yet this happy endowment ſhee had, to be very rationall according unto her conception, and would be ſet down and ſatisfied with pregnant places of Scripture being ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſſ'd and lovingly opened un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the matter of repentance much troubled her,<note place="margin">Queſt. of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed</note> that ſhe could not repent; demanding, <hi>Whether it were poſſible for her to goe to Heaven without Repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto was anſwered: Firſt,<note place="margin">Sol. <hi>I.</hi>
               </note> That God did not tie ſalvation unto any meaſure of repentance; but might at his pleaſure ſave, eſpecially where there were no
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:116556:66"/>groſſe ſinnes to dam up mercies gates; whereof praiſed bee God ſhee was free.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That God exacted no more of his creatures then he gave unto them: as the Apoſtle to the the <hi>Corinths</hi> writes, <hi>If there be firſt a willing minde, accepting of us, not according unto thoſe things we have not, but according unto thoſe things we have:</hi> And therefore, that her weak deſires and meaſure whatſoever given, might be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God. For, ſhee could not deny, but her wiſhes were that ſhe might repent, and ſhe was in ſome ſort ſorry for her indiſpoſition and hardneſſe of heart, which being a burthen and a kinde of griefe unto her, was ſo a kinde and ſore of repentance: Therefore was ſhee exhorted to be patient, and not to limite the Holy One of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:116556:66"/>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> nor preſcribe the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and depth of all wiſedome which were the beſt way to bring her unto Heaven; but to ſubmit her ſelfe unto the good pleaſure of God; truſt, hope with the beſt, and uſe the meanes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Further alleadging un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, That it was not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, number or continuance of our ſinnes that could ſtop mercy from us; but finall impenitency and obduration.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Repentance being the gift of God, which hee might at his pleaſure give and accept in good part whatſoever meaſure thereof he were pleaſed: It was not to be doubted of, but that ſhe might in time attaine unto ſo much thereof in the uſe of meanes, as hee would accept of, and as might bring her unto heaven. For
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:116556:67"/>God of all his Attributes is ſaid only to delight in mercy, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. his nature being to forgive and forget iniquity, tranſgreſſion, ſin and ſinnes of cuſtome.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That as ſinne was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall act in us, ſo in God there was a perpetuall act in pardoning of ſinne, not tranſient, but in a perpetuall conſtant current; as <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1. <hi>a fountaine opened, ever running, to waſh away all ſinne and uncleanneſſes;</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the like things, which now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine wonne her ſpirit to reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God; though now and then upon divers occaſions ſhe uſed to fly out a little: Yet being continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally hammered and hewen with the tough acute diſputations of this good man, Mr <hi>Hooker,</hi> who was very aſſiduouſly induſtrious in watching her diſpoſition, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:116556:67"/>various inclinations of her changes and tentations; by Gods mercy ſhee grew ſtill better, uſing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent her ſelfe conſtantly to the uſe of meanes: having prayer, cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing, expounding and reading of the word, and ſinging of Pſalms conſtantly in the family, now with delight and willingneſſe acted: being never weary to have the word expounded; yea, and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſpending ſome time by her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone daily; as the indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her diſtempered body, heart-burning and in a manner perpetuall head-ach, would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her; but yet would not bee known nor confeſſe unto any what in private ſhee did being alone.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The good ſoule is yet toſſed up and down.</note>Now have wee her in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe <hi>toſſed up and downe, like the Church in their march unto Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:116556:68"/>fraught with divers ſtormes, now backwards, now forwards, with many turning and winding temptations, reſtleſſe in her thoughts, becauſe (deſire hath no reſt) having ſome glimmering glimpſe of hope, but (as ſhe faid) had no grounds for the ſame, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting when the Lord would bee pleaſed to work in her ſome great work for enabling. In which Caſe, now up, now down, <hi>the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhee grew in her minde, having ſtill therewithall the greater weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and indiſpoſition of body,</hi> ſhe continued a long time, her old friend Mr <hi>Dod</hi> now and then once in a quarter of a year comming to viſite her, whom ſhe much rejoyced to ſee, praying not any more to ſtay ſo long away; for now ſhee reſted aſſured her time on earth was but of ſmall continuance.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:116556:68"/>About which time it fell out, that Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> alſo having acted his part with her, and done his beſt, to comfort, uphold and rectifie her ſpirit, ſo fitting her for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as nothing remained to bee done but a full gaile of ſpirituall winde to blow upon her, to bring forth her fruit, that by Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence he was married unto her waiting-woman: After which both of them having lived ſome time after with her, and he cal'd to bee Lecturer at <hi>Chemsford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maſter Hooker leaves her.</note> they both left her, her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band having provided another for the Cure, but not like unto the other; who alſo came often to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite her, being much there. And there lived alſo two miles from thence, a worthy good Miniſter, one Mr <hi>Witherell</hi> of <hi>Waltham</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Thames,</hi> whom ſhee went con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:116556:69"/>to heare, and was alwayes very helpfull unto her (but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> had thus left her) whom every Thurſday ſhee heard, hee being a painfull, able, good mercifull man, did then much help her, both in publike, and alſo in private helps of conference and expounding of the Word, which now ſhee much delighted in at all occaſions; eſpecially ſhee found a little comfort in opening of that chapter <hi>Micah</hi> 7. one time when Mr <hi>Dod</hi> was with her three Moneths before her death, though (as ſhee ſaid) ſhe durſt not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge nor confeſſe the ſame for feare it had not been ſo.</p>
            <p>But ah, ſhould I now lance forth into the diſcourſe of the loſſe of ſo good a friend?<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration unto her death.</note> but what ſay I of loſſe? <hi>No, ſhe was not loſt, ſhee was now found with
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:116556:69"/>her face ſtrongly bent home Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards:</hi> Having therefore thus far proceeded in this ſaid <hi>Trage-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall</hi> diſcourſe, I muſt now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> thereof: If therefore good Reader, thou wilt have a little more patience to heare the reſt, thou ſhalt quickly ſee the <hi>Scene change</hi> with a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Comicall</hi> concluſion: For though all this while ſhee hath gone forth weeping carrying pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſeed, <hi>now thou ſhalt ſee ber returne with ſheaves of everlaſting joy;</hi> though weeping hath beene many an evening, <hi>yet now thou ſhalt ſee joy come in an everlaſting morning.</hi> Though Satan hath much toyled, wearied out and vexed her ſpirit, <hi>yet thou ſhalt ſee how the God of peace ſhall ſhortly tread downe Satan under her feet:</hi> her reward infinitely ſurpaſſing all her
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:116556:70"/>momentany ſufferings; which now comes to bee the fourth and laſt thing propounded, <hi>Her death, and the preparation unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divers years ſince Mr <hi>Dod</hi> left her, and ſome large time alſo after that Mr <hi>Hooker</hi> was removed unto <hi>Chemsford,</hi> ſhee remained more chearefull in minde, though tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with her heart-burning and in a manner perpetuall <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum,</hi> which made her to lie much of the day upon her bed, unfit for any other actions of endeavor in the uſe of meanes ſhe would or ſhould otherwiſe be employed in. About this time a ſtrong diſtaſte was given her from a neare friend,<note place="margin">A new griefe is added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</note> (not neceſſary here to relate, nor to our purpoſe:) Which yet faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo upon her, that it grew more and more, and brought her into a poſture of great diſcontent, ſo as
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:116556:70"/>ſhee became in her thoughts a woman in ſome ſort of another world; who being reſolute in her way, unremoveable, having reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and alwayes purpoſing, when ſhee found her ſelfe neare unto her laſt, to die at her Fathers Houſe, and lie with her kindred and friends at <hi>Ammerſum, Shee ſuddenly told her Husband, that ſhee found her ſelfe very ill, and therefore that ſhee was purpoſed to goe ſuddenly unto her Fathers Houſe:</hi> Hee much wondering at the ſuddenneſſe of her reſolution, told her, If her reſolution were ſuch, to goe ſo quickly, his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was ſuch as hee could not yet goe with her, unleſſe ſhe would ſtay until his buſineſſe was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatcht; but if ſhe were reſolute to goe, that hee would not ſtay her, ſhe might when ſhe would.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:116556:71"/>So ſhee being reſolute, the next day with two of her men ſhee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted for her Fathers Houſe, where being arrived, they wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that ſhee came ſo without her Husband, ſhee in plaine termes told them, <hi>That ſhee alwayes had reſolved to die at</hi> Sharolois, <hi>and therefore ſhee not knowing how long her time ſhould be, finding her weakneſſe great, had now come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her husband to die there,</hi> ſaying, <hi>that her husband would ſhortly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They much wondering at this ſudden newes from her, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected ſtrange ſpeeches; yet at her comming ſmoothed her over, telling her that this was but ſome unwarranted feare had ſurprized her, and that ſhe would finde her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe herein as in many other ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed things deceived. But ſhee
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:116556:71"/>ſtill maintained the maine, that her time was at hand, and ſhe very weak, though ſhee carryed it faire; after which her Husband in a week or ten dayes arrived: But the poſture of her carriage for all this was the ſame, <hi>She being in a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsing extraordinary ſtrange hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of talking of the beſt things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually night and day without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſsion, not having any jot of ſleep almoſt night or day;</hi> whereby her ſpirits were both much ſpent and tyred out.</p>
            <p>The Relator who ſtill had a watchfull eye upon all the paſſages of her occurrences,<note place="margin">Mr Dod is gone for to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her once more</note> knowing of her late diſcontent and cauſe thereof, and hearing that ſhe was removed to <hi>Sharolois,</hi> made no more adoe, but with all haſte went and brought Mr <hi>Dod</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fearing that this might
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:116556:72"/>prove his laſt journey unto her (as indeed it proved,) when he came unto her two Sundayes before her death, he by that time found her <hi>much weakned in body, keeping her bed; but with ſuch vehement deſires to diſcourſe of, and heare of the beſt things, reading, expounding and ſinging of Pſalmes, that all were ſtruck with admiration:</hi> and would not ſtay with her ſo long, as ſhee would have had us; nor read unto her, becauſe we would gladly have had her to reſt, which could not be done; for <hi>ſhee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſtill ſpeaking both night and day to ſome one or other who watched with her, yet all of the beſt things;</hi> for her time being ſhort, ſhe imagined (as ſhee ſaid) <hi>ſhee could not too advantagiouſly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of the two Sundayes
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:116556:72"/>before her death,<note place="margin">Shee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares her children, to beare her death</note> ſhee would not ſuffer her children to goe to Church that day, but made them ſtay with her, to inſtruct them, and ſpeak her minde unto them, alledging that ſhee muſt take time whilſt ſhee had time; for, ſhe knew not whether or not ſhee ſhould live untill the next Sunday: when ſhee vented unto them in the beſt manner ſhee could at large, all ſhee had to ſay unto them, expounding divers Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures unto them, formerly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto her (which ſhee had a large ſtrong memory to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) this day finiſhing all ſhee had to ſay unto them, ſaving at laſt to give them her bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Now the Munday after this, was all ſpent in continuall confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> ſo much as he would conferre with her, for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:116556:73"/>feare of over-toyling her ſpirits, ſhee being in the other extremity more forward to entertaine and ſpeak of the beſt things,<note place="margin">A ſtrange change.</note> then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſhee had beene backwards; which ſhewed ſome ſtrange change at hand: yet all this while could ſhee, or would ſhee never ſleep, night or day, but in a perpetuall motion of ſpeaking of variety of all ſorts of things; but by her good-will, ſtill of Divinity, and of the life to come, undervaluing all this world, and eating ſparingly.</p>
            <p>On the Tueſday next in the morning ſhee ſent for Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> who prayed and talkt a while with her, with variety of excellent diſcourſe of death, heaven and eternall glory; when ſuddenly as prayer was done, about eight of the clock in the morning we were ſtrangely enterrupted by a ſtrange
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:116556:73"/>and uncouth out-cry which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from her, I am aſſured the like was never heard or read of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: which uncouth language (in ſhew a rapture of another world) a few words whereof the Relator can ſhew or expreſſe, onely he hopes the Reader will pardon him, if he miſſe in recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting things of another world, which <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe was at a non-plus in after his rapture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.7. and <hi>Peter</hi> alſo after his deſcent from the Mount, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.6. not knowing what he ſaid: So difficult it is to expreſſe things unutterable.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">A ſtrange Rapture of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note>Oh, oh, oh, what's this, what's this, what's this? I am undone, undone, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, I cannot endure it,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:116556:74"/>endure it: O, ô, ô, let me be gone, let me be gone, ô, I muſt be gone, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tarry, I cannot tarry; ô what ſhall I doe? what ſhall I doe? O Father, O Mother, O Husband, kiſſe me, kiſſe me, and let me bee gone: Come all, farewell all, let me take you by the hand and bee gone: Lo, lo, the Angels are come, they wait, they ſtay for mee; O deare Mother! why hold you me? I muſt be gone: O,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:116556:74"/>he is come, he is come, he is come: Now you have it, you have it, you have it, why hold you me? let me be gone, my work is done: O call, call, call, where is my Crowne? fetch mee my Crowne: Bring, bring, bring mee my white Robes, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, quickly, quickly, why run you not? The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſtay, now you have it, you have it, you have it. (Meaning that now wee had the iſſue and fruit of all our Prayers) O, it overcomes, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:116556:75"/>overcomes me; I am undone, undone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; what ſhall I doe? what ſhall I doe? what ſhall I doe? O you will not let me be gone.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>With innumerable ſuch ſwift ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions could not bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, ſhee in that ſhort time of halfe a quarter of an houre ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more then one can treatably in an houre, with an incredible ſwitneſſe (no ordinary action of this life) <hi>when withall ſhee heaved and heaved up ſtill all the time with fixed eyes towards the houſe top, as though ſhee had ſeene ſome Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and would have flown away from them all, making a hole through the chamber Roofe:</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:116556:75"/>which time (as wee cannot blame them;) the poſture of all the Spectators was (ſave her Husband who went weeping and wringing his hands up and down the Chamber) ſilence, wonder, and admiration; they in all their life time having never ſeene or heard of the like: Which put Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> her Husband, and all of them to a non-plus (as being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all experience:) But if the Reader will have patience, this good Creature ſhall her ſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound this rare Riddle, yea, and comment upon it.</p>
            <p>This fit of ſudden, extreame, raviſhing unſupportable joy, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſtrength of mortality to retaine or belong capable of) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, and ſhee layd againe; who formerly had ſtriven to have got away from them all; they
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:116556:76"/>all being in an amazed aſtoniſhed ſilence; ſhee her ſelfe began thus? <hi>Why are you all ſilent?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her ſpeech af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her Rapture.</note> 
               <hi>where is</hi> Mr <hi>Dod?</hi> Who being neere unto her, ſat down on the beds ſide by her, unto whom ſhee thus directed her ſpeech, <hi>Sir, what did you think of mee lately in this ſtrange poſture I have been in? did not you imagine me to have been mad all the time?</hi> Mr <hi>Dod</hi> Replyed, No, but that it was very ſtrange unto them all, having never heard or ſeene the like. So (ſaid ſhe) <hi>ſurely it was, it was very ſtrange, But will you know how it ſurprized mee? As this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ere you came to prayer, I being alone prayed to God that hee would not abſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for ever: but that that once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my death, hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale Chriſt unto mee, give mee
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:116556:76"/>ſome ſenſe and feeling of his love:</hi> And open the brazen Gates of his hard heart of mine, that the King of glory might enter in. <hi>After which as you had prayed, this ſudden out-crying fit of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable joy and feeling ſurprized mee with ſuch violence ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon me, as I could not containe my ſelfe, but make this ſudden out-cry amongſt you all: But I muſt confeſſe unto you, I know not, neither doe I remember what I ſaid: But now I beſeech you to make this uſe hereof hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unto all in my Caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Triumphant rare Speech and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> After mee never diſpaire of any, how deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:116556:77"/>miſerable ſo ever their <hi>Caſe</hi> bee (which at the worſt cannot exceed mine) but uſe and apply the meanes unto them, and they will prevaile at length. I was like a piece of knotty timber, who have endured ſo many the more knocks with ſtrong wedges, ſo much adoe there was ſo work me; but now I thank God, who hath heard my prayer and revealed Chriſt unto me, and now
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:116556:77"/>I care not for all this world: The fountaine of all my miſery hath been, that I ſought for that in the Law which I ſhould have found in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and for that in my ſelfe which was only to be found in Chriſt. A wrong way I confeſſe, which hath occaſioned unto me ſo much ſorrow; but now all is well; O pray, pray, pray, O give thanks; for, now you have it, you have it, you have it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:116556:78"/>
            <p>This ſo ſolid and ſtrange ſpeech, ſo heavenly, rationall, gave a great deale of contentment unto all preſent; Mr <hi>Dod</hi> according unto her deſire, framing himſelfe unto a prayer altogether of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, admiring Gods infinite work in her, and for her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching a happy cloſe of this great work begun: For matter of petition now ſhee cared not for, lying like a Conqueror, with an extraordinary cheerefull aſpect, full of rapt joy, as now ſhee had been poſſeſſor of all things, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no need of any thing; now that Chriſt was hers, all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hers alſo; the remainder of the day being ſpent in over-joyed ſpeeches, with exhortations to Thankſgiving; ſtill telling us, <hi>Now you have it, yee have it, you have it:</hi> and taking our hands
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:116556:78"/>in hers, and heaving them up and down many times together very thankfull unto us all, as ſhee wiſhed us to bee thankfull unto God for her.</p>
            <p>This ſame Tueſday,<note place="margin">She bath the like Rapture againe.</note> again about foure a clock in the afternoone, the Chamber being full of her friends, joyfull to ſee her ſo fraught with joy, after ſo many ſorrowfull dayes: Suddenly ſhee fell out againe, in a ſtrange man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in ſuch an other rapt fit of joy, beyond all expreſſion, utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt about the ſame things as formerly, in the ſame manner as in the morning, enduring about the ſame time; and ſo ceaſed and was quiet againe as formerly: She thereupon called Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at the ſtrangeneſſe of the thing, told him, That <hi>her joy and ſenſe thereof, was ſo over-comming
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:116556:79"/>and ſtrong, as ſhee could not for her life containe her ſelfe, from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting forth thus againe; for as ſhee ſaid her fraile fleſh was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come therewith;</hi> and ſo ſhee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating him again to give thanks, he did ſo, ſpending the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that day in heavenly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of another world; hoping that ſhee ſhould that night have ſlept ſoundly, having now watched and been without ſleep, above a week together: But it ſeemes, as as the lame man, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.8. having received his feet, for joy did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for awhile but skip, frisk, and leap; ſo ſhee now having been as it were in another world, revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with uncouth new joyes, could not take any reſt or ſleep, but rejoyce alwayes and talke of the ſame. And ſo that night having divers friends to watch
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:116556:79"/>and ſit by her, ſhee ſpent the ſame in good diſcourſe and ſinging of Pſalmes.</p>
            <p>All the time ſhee had been ill, ſhee could not of all the Pſalmes endure to joyn in ſinging of the thirty Pſalme, but that night of her ſelfe ſhe cal'd for it, with this expreſſion, <hi>Couſin now turn to the thirty Pſalme</hi> (by the Relator al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes urged upon her to belong unto her) but I durſt never appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate or apply the ſame unto my ſelfe, untill now, and ſo that Tueſday night ſung the ſame very cheerefully, as was ſaid, ſhe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this night over alſo without any inclination to reſt or ſleep.</p>
            <p>On the Wedneſday morning,<note place="margin">Her dreſſing for the grave.</note> her indulgent Mother, that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy good ſoule Mr <hi>Tottle,</hi> did riſe betimes and came to viſite her, when finding her in a ſtrange
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:116556:80"/>unuſuall Attire, for that morning (now apprehending death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at hand) ſhe had cauſed her ſelfe to be dreſſed from top to toe all in white, concealing her conceit therein untill her Mother came; who ſeeing her thus ſtrangely dreſt, ſpake lovingly unto her in her accuſtomed phraſe: How now Daughter, what's the matter with thee? me thinks thou lookeſt like a Bride, <hi>So I am Mother</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>a Bride now trimmed for Chriſt the Bridegroome, and now Mother I have my laſt ſuit to make unto you (for I am a woman of another world) when I am dead, I pray you, dreſſe me juſt thus as you ſee me now, and ſo let me be laid in my grave; for, for this cauſe, I cauſed my ſelf to be dreſſed thus this morning, that you might ſee how I would be laid in the grave:</hi> Whereunto her
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:116556:80"/>Mother burſting forth into weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhee comforted her all ſhee could, ſaying, <hi>Mother, me thinks you ſhould rather rejoyce to ſee me ſo neare home, after that I have ſo long a time been ſtorm beaten and ſea-ſick, not now to grudge that I am arrived ſo neare the haven:</hi> And ſo prayd her to ſuffer her willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to depart home in peace: whereupon her Mother for that time (being a matchleſſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mother) parted with many teares.</p>
            <p>Soone after this came Mr <hi>Dod</hi> and Dr <hi>Preſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> to her, unto whom ſhe with a great deale of joy told the ſame diſcourſe as formerly ſhe had done unto her Mother, <hi>That thus as ſhee was then dreſt, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be laid in the grave:</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their departure having prayed with her and given thanks (for no
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:116556:81"/>other part of prayer ſhee now affected, as being heire of all things, not having need of any thing) ſhee ſent for divers of the houſe ſeverally,<note place="margin">Shee ſchooles the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</note> unto whom ſhee gave ſeaſonable and ſutable exho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, fitting unto their places, thaking her leave of them all; wherein ſhee was ſo punctuall, that with her good will ſhe would have had every ſervant of the houſe to have come ſeverally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her; but that her Mother fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that which after came to paſſe, ſome weakneſſe to enſue ſo much watching, ſpeaking and toyling inceſſantly of her ſpirits, durſt not expoſe her unto the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of ſo inſupportable a toyle.</p>
            <p>Being now very much ſpent, this Wedneſday after dinner, ſhee cauſed to voide her Chamber of every body, and ſent for her
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:116556:81"/>Father to ſpeak with, ſchoole, and take leave of him; whom ſhee dealt with and ſchooled (having him all alone) for above an houre together;<note place="margin">Shee chooles and takes leave of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> whom when ſhee had ſaid her minde unto, and taken her leave of, ſhee diſmiſſed him. At his deſcending from her, the Relator did what hee could in a a faire way to have fiſhed from him, what ſhe had ſaid unto him: Of whom nothing could bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſave in the generall, <hi>That ſhee had given him very good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, both touching his wife and himſelfe, and concerning the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his eſtate and family, and to keep a Preacher in his houſe;</hi> with many other, all good things, as hee ſaid.</p>
            <p>Preſently after this ſhee called to ſpeak with the Relator,<note place="margin">Her farewell, ſpeech to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator.</note> whom having made to ſit down by her,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:116556:82"/>ſhee firſt gave him many ſolemne thanks in a ſull gaile of loving expreſſions for his care and paines taken with her; and then ſhe ſaid ſhe had a ſuit unto him: Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that any ſuit of hers, if in his power, was granted ere known; which yet ſerved not the turne, but ſhee would have his hand to forgive her; which being done, ſhe prayed him <hi>to forgive her;</hi> who wondering at the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this needleſſe ſuit, told her, that hee had rather cauſe to ask forgiveneſſe of her, having much failed both in duty and love unto her:<note place="margin">A rare confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>O no, ſaid ſhee, you muſt forgive me that you for ſo many yeares together having ſhewed mee ſo much love, and beene a meanes of my everlaſting comfort and happineſſe, that yet I have been ſo unkind unto you, for
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:116556:82"/>I have not loved you by the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred part, in that meaſure I ought to have done, according to that love you have ſhewed mee: But will you know the cauſe? I could love no body as I ſhould ſo long as I was not aſſured of Gods love to me (for that onely ſets our love a fire to runne ſtrongly the right way) I could untill then neither love you nor any body elſe, during ſo much diſtraction and diverſion as I ſhould have done: And now that my love is thus kindled, this is my ſorrow (my time being ſhort) that now I can no otherwiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my ſelfe then by this poore acknowledgement, in a time I am ſo unfit and diſabled to performe my deſires: But I well hope, that what I cannot doe, that God who ſet you a work for my good, and my other friends will performe, when I
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:116556:83"/>am gone:</hi> And ſo for that time with abundance of love and thanks diſmiſſed the Relator.</p>
            <p>Thus having in ſome ample manner diſpoſed of all the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhee ſeemed to have in this world: The remainder of this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone ſhee lay in her former joyfull poſture, rejoycing to ſpeak of the beſt things unto every one neare unto her; yet without any reſt or ſleep, or inclination that way. When Mr <hi>Dod</hi> and Dr <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> came to viſite her, ſhee ſtill entreating to give thanks, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe ſhee had, as want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing: So continuing all this day, untill the evening late, that there was a great change, as in part ſhall be ſhewed; for leaſt ſhee ſhould bee lifted up through her former revelation, joyes and rapture, ſo ſhort which endured
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:116556:83"/>not, ſurpaſſing her ſtrength, ſhee had a weakning cooler to keep her down low.</p>
            <p>For, lo, lo,<note place="margin">Shee is ſurpriſed with a weakneſs.</note> 
               <hi>the Scene now changes againe, the curtaine waves and toſſes a little with an uncouth winde, party coloured, no firme im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions appeared:</hi> She who lately was in a glorious triumph, flying away forcibly from us all, as it were with Eagles wings mounting upwards, is now ſuddenly ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with an extreame fainting and weakneſſe of ſpirits, being for ten dayes and nights over-wearied, watched and toyled out, ſo as now ſhee bewrayed ſome weakneſſe in her expreſſions, not being as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſo lively and ſubſtantiall; which continued the Thurſday and Friday after, never having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſt or ſleep all the time; which diſtemper, made them ſend
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:116556:84"/>poſt to <hi>London</hi> for two Phyſitians, hoping by their advice to have made her reſt: But all in vaine, <hi>No phyſick could cure her but heavenly physick:</hi> Therefore on the Saturday, Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> Dr <hi>Preſton,</hi> and Mr <hi>Hooker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Faſt kept for her.</note> kept a private faſt for her; the iſſue whereof was, in that forenoone ſhe fell aſleep, reſted ſoundly ſome five or ſix houres together, and then waked in a very midle gentle temper. Then ſhee cal'd unto her Couſin <hi>Herreis</hi> (a good Gentlewoman, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes exceeding carefull of her) <hi>Sarah, tell me, did not I lately in ſome ſpeeches forget my ſelfe?</hi> Whereunto her Anſwer was, Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Couſin ſo you did, but we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted the ſame to your many dayes and night-watching, and over-wearying of your ſpirits, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſo long to hold out: So it
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:116556:84"/>was, ſaid ſhe, <hi>My ſpirits were ſpent and gone, which cauſed that weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſhee remembring all that had paſſed,<note place="margin">Her death.</note> her ſtrange Raptures, (but nothing which then ſhee had ſaid in them) retaining her former grounds, comfort and cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (as in ſo much weakneſſe could bee expreſſed) cald for Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> Dr <hi>Preſton,</hi> with the reſt of her friends, cauſing them to give thanks with her, and for her, venting her ſelfe unto them thus, <hi>That her time was now at hand, prayd them not to leave her, and being very weak, ſpake then her minde unto her Father, Mother, and Husband, in a ſort taking leave of them, ſent for her Children, and bleſſed them, now imagining to have done all her work:</hi> And ſo from thence fell into
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:116556:85"/>a ſilent Rapture of joyfull ſinging of Hymnes, and verſes of Pſalms, not greatly caring to ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any body, ſave now and then unto Mr <hi>Dod</hi> when hee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an occaſion: And ſo ſhee lay this Saturday night, and the next Sunday, only when Mr <hi>Dod</hi> came deſiring ſtill to give thanks, all which time ſhee grew weaker and weaker, having by this time no audible but a hollow low voyce, ſcarce to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>The Munday after in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when ſhee fell aſleep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, Mr <hi>Dod</hi> with the reſt comming unto her, ſhee when ſhee ſaw them all about her, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced and ſmiled, taking them all by the hand with a cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full countenance, beckned unto Maſter <hi>Dod</hi> to give thanks, and bent her ſelfe what ſhee could
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:116556:85"/>with lifted up hands to joyne, ſpeaking ſoftly unto her ſelfe in her Hymning way: And ſo whilſt they were at Prayer, ſuddenly her hands falling, and her lips going, ſhe ſunck down in the bed and departed, leaving all her friends mourning about her.</p>
            <p>Thus have we ſeene the ſtrange Story, and ſcarce credible, the like never heard of before I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, of this good Gentlewoman, whom now wee will ſuffer to reſt in peace, freed from all the ſtormes and tempeſts wherein ſhee left her ſurvivers,<note place="margin">Her bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall.</note> 
               <hi>Who two dayes after was buried according to her deſire at</hi> Ammerſum, <hi>in that Attire ſhee before her death had dreſſed her ſelfe; Dr</hi> Preſton <hi>Preaching her funerall Sermon,</hi> with the infinite teares of all her friends and poore of the Pariſh.</p>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:116556:86"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Shee was of an extraordinary ſincere, plaine, true heart; full and abounding in love, mervellous ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret in all her goodneſſe, very charitable to the poore, of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable converſation and life; and the beſt Anti-hypocrite</hi> (Chriſt excepted) <hi>that ever lived; for, ſhe alwayes wore her worſt ſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and wonderfully clock'd all the good things ſhee ever did or ſaid; with all her skill endevouring to extenuate all ſhee this way did or ſaid:</hi> Of her jewels and other things her Husband lovingly gave her way to diſpoſe of, ſhee left Legacies and remembrances un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all her friends who had beene moſt helpfull unto her: and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhillings a piece unto ſome few good poor women, whom ſhe had ſecretly, unknown unto any, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to pray conſtantly for her.</p>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:116556:86"/>
            <p>And now that we have brought this good Creature into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, god Reader give mee leave, out of all which hath been ſaid (for memories ſake) to ſum up briefly her grand <hi>Caſe;</hi> leaſt it ſhould be miſtaken.</p>
            <p>A good Creature, in her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall eſtate,<note place="margin">The ſum of this grand Caſe.</note> qualified with the beſt of meere natures endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; accidentally encountring with ſome grand difficulties, which a little overcame her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural parts. By the way, being ſurprized with admiration and wonder at the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ſome eminent Profeſſors her Neighbours (the reflex where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſtruck her with a ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, not to be yet the ſame, as to bee ſaved ſhee muſt needs bee) with her other concurring croſſes, wrought ſo upon her, as
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:116556:87"/>ſhee became very melancholy, yet with an enforced mirth to cloke the ſame; which advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage Satan eſpying (who ſtill loves to work out his ends by that dolefull temper) he aſſaults her with fearefull night-dreames, ſeconded with divers wilde-fire temptations to have driven her unto finall diſpaire, which hee had well neare effected. Meane while God intending to make her an everlaſting monument of his mercy, intending a great work unto others by her trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and deliverance; to convert by the way her Husband and Parents with divers others in both Families (ſo ſtopping di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers gaps with one buſh) and (as hee alwayes doth, and hath done) to over-ſhoot Satan in his own Bow; provides and ſends
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:116556:87"/>one of a thouſand to finde her out, wraſtle with all her temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, foyle Satan, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince her judgement; ſo draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her unto a conformity of the meanes; though with much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. But yet ſo, as an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall indiſpoſition ſhee had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired (ſpiced with the dregges of remaining temptations) kept her off from endeavour, never all this time having had any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or feeling, without paines taking for it, in the interim ſhee is well beaten; <hi>God at length yeelding unto the importunity of prayers for her, affords her ſuch an immenſe meaſure of comfort and feeling for a ſmall time, as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality was incapble to retaine:</hi> After which (her ſpirits thereby vanquiſhed) out-wearied with
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:116556:88"/>watching and inceſſant ſpeaking for divers dayes and nights to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for a ſmall time ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayes ſome weakneſſe. But up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a private Faſt kept for her two dayes before her death, ſhee revives againe, maintaines her grounds, former joyes and feeling; from thence untill her death, remaining in a ſilent Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of joyes; wherein ſhee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: <hi>leaving her ſelfe, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver memorable mirror of Gods wonderfull mercies, unto all the ſtiffe, obdurate, hard-hearted for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, good Reader, tell mee, Is it fit or poſſible that we ſhould part with ſo grand, ſtrange, rare, and matchleſſe a <hi>CASE,</hi> without ſome briefe uſe thereof unto the Survivers? for which cauſe it hath beene
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:116556:88"/>written, and for ought wee know, all her ſufferings were: O no, courage then, hold out a little, and I will now diſpatch briefly, endeavouring in the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophe</hi> of this our <hi>Tragi-Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> to recompence thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with the fragrances of ſome ſweet ſmelling cloſe of ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine rarities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> Firſt, Then here wee may learne, <hi>That not the great things of this world makes one happy, but the favour of the great God:</hi> Nothing being able to content the ſoule, but that which is able to fill it, which all this world cannot doe: Shewing that there is nothing ſuch in theſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things (as wee imagine) in the evill day or times of tryall. Witneſſe this good Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the ſubject of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:116556:89"/>who might have ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the fulneſſe of all earthly pleaſures; all which were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unto her, ſhee was dampt in the midſt of all; ſo as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could revive or joy her (like unto <hi>David</hi>) ſave the light of Gods countenance to be lifted up upon her. And therefore, not to deceive our ſelves, but to ſettle in our judgements, that wherein onely true ſolid laſting happineſſe conſiſts, <hi>the favour of God,</hi> and follow that with all our might.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Then ſee hence, <hi>That of all the Burthens in this world, ſinne is the moſt inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, eſpecially when therewith in any meaſure is joyned a ſenſe of the wrath of God:</hi> For if God, as it is in <hi>Amos,</hi> complaine, that hee is preſſed down under the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:116556:89"/>ſame, as a Cart under the ſheaves, the ſenſe thereof alſo making <hi>David</hi> to roare for griefe of heart, having alſo bred ſo much terror, amazement and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto this good Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for ſo many yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being free of groſſe ſinnes; what may they think of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who goe on ſinning! with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, living and going on in groſſer ſins without repentance?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Here we may ſee, <hi>That in the beſt, where there is ſinne, there muſt and will bee ſmarting puniſhments, though it be forgiven as</hi> Davids <hi>was:</hi> Yet we may ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be beaten for the ſame, he taking vengeance of our inventions, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks: for this good Gentlewoman, though ſaved and forgiven, yet was ſoundly beaten ere ſhee departed hence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:116556:90"/>to bee afraid to ſinne, and to ſtand in awe of the anger of the great God; for though hee may forgive, yet if hee open Hell unto us, keep us in perpetuall fear as upon the rack, as he did this good Gentlewoman, letting Satan looſe to buffet her, oh what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort can we have in ſuch a tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting dying life? having our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe hid from our eyes?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Hence alſo we may learn, <hi>That the more beloved, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the ſoundlier beaten, ſifted and tried,</hi> Amos 3. You only have I known, of all the Nations of the Earth, therefore you ſhall not goe unpuniſhed for all your iniquities; wherefore corrections being a ſign of love, not of reprobation (as the Devill perſwades) that the Saints ſhould not be diſcouraged though ſtorme-beaten in their journey
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:116556:90"/>homewards; they may goe to Heaven for all this, as this good Gentlewoman did.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, And ſo here alſo we may gather <hi>what need we have of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to have its perfect work in us, to fit us for the greateſt and moſt ſmarting afflictions:</hi> there being yet ſome light in this darke cloud; <hi>the ſoreſt and moſt ſmarting croſſes, ending uſually in the greateſt and moſt glorious deliverances:</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the none-ſuch troubles of <hi>Iacob, Ioſeph, Iob, David,</hi> the Churches forty years Pilgrimage in the Wilderneſſe, &amp; of this good Gentlewoman, all ending in peace and joy; becauſe the promiſe is, <hi>that of neceſsity, the patient abiding of the righteous muſt needs end in joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Then alſo we ſee here, that <hi>croſſes and afflictions are only leſſer and greater, as it pleaſes the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:116556:91"/>great God to ſet them on leſſe or more:</hi> as it pleaſes him to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract the light of his countenance from us, turn looſe Satan upon us, enfatuate our judgements, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us ſome taſte and ſenſe of his encenſed wrath: Oh! who then can dwell with ſuch everlaſting burnings? and if ſmaler ſins diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered thus ſet on and torment, yea, ſome thoughts only, as in this good Gentlewoman; Oh! what may the greater doe, if he ſhould aggravate them, diſcovering the wrath due unto them, without a ſuitable ſight of mercy? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to break off our ſins betimes, repent of them, and to ſow for our ſelves in righteouſneſſe, that wee may have a ſure reward, and bee able at laſt to ſtand with boldneſſe before the Son of Man.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, So <hi>ſeeing too eager de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:116556:91"/>of feeling coſt this Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo deare though ſhee had her deſire, therefore not to dote too much upon it;</hi> being reſtleſſe untill they have it, as many good ſoules doe, who like <hi>Rachel</hi> reſtleſſe for children, cryd out ſtill, <hi>comfort, comfort, feeling feeling,</hi> or elſe wee die: But let them be contented of what meaſure thereof God of his infinite wiſedome thinks beſt for them: For, <hi>He who hath created them for eternity of glory, ſurely knowes the beſt meanes and way to bring them thither:</hi> Seeing, feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the beſt is uncertaine, ſhort and quickly vaniſhing; <hi>and too much doted upon and eagerly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, brings us onely to a habit of diſcontentment without it:</hi> whilſt wee cannot bee contented unleſſe every day the Almighty feaſt us, forgetting that wee walk by faith,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:116556:92"/>and not by ſight; and that the life we now live in the fleſh is by the Faith of the Son of God; viſion and ſenſe, for to come.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Then behold from this rare experience here this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Not to preſcribe or appoint God a way which way to bring us unto glory;</hi> Hee knew the fitteſt and ſhorteſt way to have brought the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> unto the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> without paſſing through a red ſea: But out of his infinite wiſedome, he made choyce of the wilderneſſe way unto them, That (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhewes) <hi>hee might prove them, try them and doe them good at their latter end:</hi> And yet how crooked ſoever his wayes ſeem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our corrupted ſenſes, they bee alwayes ſtraight, how full ſoever of turnings and windings; as the Pſalmiſts, <hi>That hee brought them
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:116556:92"/>out by a right way unto Canaan:</hi> Therefore to reſt confident herein, that this which God appoints is alwayes beſt for us; whether hee lead us in a wilderneſſe, in a a ſtraight, crooked, ſmooth, tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous long afflicted way, by the gates of Hell unto Heaven, or with a more gentle comfortable gale of joy; let us be contented, ſo he bring us thither, as hee did this good woman here; if by any meanes wee attaine unto a joyfull Reſurrection of the Dead, it is a very great purchaſe as <hi>Paul</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, For (which is the next) Sure it is, <hi>Seeing a glance of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a little taſte of heavenly joy is ſo prevalent to make us to forget all, even an age of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as this good Gentlewoman found, who thereupon forgot all her
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:116556:93"/>by-paſt troubles ſwallowed up in ſurmounting joyes;</hi> I ſay, if a touch, a taſte, a ſhort glance onely bee ſo forcible and raviſhing, <hi>How ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mountingly excellent glorious and reviſhing ſhall that eſtate bee to drink at the fountaine head of the beatificall viſion, out of the rivers of his pleaſures for ever?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to reſt confident and patient in all afflictions, ſeeing our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are at length beyond all our croſſes; ſeeing <hi>God ruines none by afflictions,</hi> but purges, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, cleanſes, whitens, enlightens and fits us thereby to bee veſſels capacious of ſo much the more glory; out of the ruines of the fleſh, erecting, framing and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up that glorious ſtructure of the new creature, to mount up at length out of the wilderneſſe of this world, fraught with Myrrhe
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:116556:93"/>and Frankincenſe, and all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Merchant, unto eternity of glory for ever.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, Next hence obſerve, <hi>That God never comes too late unto his ſervants, but will alwayes bee ſeene in the Mount, making our extremities his opportunities:</hi> as he did unto <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s caſe, and as this good Gentlewoman found, who being much afflicted, comfortleſſe for many yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, even at the point of death: yet at length hee was entreated, came and revived her, in a ſwifter courſe then the running ſwift Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets of <hi>Aminadab:</hi> nay, came flying as it were upon the wings of the winde, paſſing ans skipping by all the hills of ſinnes and mountaines of her corruptions; when (in her appearing laſt ſuit unto him, and extreame weakneſſe) ſhe had beg's
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:116556:94"/>now at length once before her death <hi>to open the brazen gates of her hard heart, that the King of glory might enter in;</hi> which was abundantly done. Therefore, though he ſtay never ſo long, let all the hard-hearted gaine by this experience of hers; with the Churches reſolution in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> I will wait upon him who hides his face from the houſe of <hi>Iacob;</hi> and I will look for him; and reaſon good, For <hi>he never failes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, being waited for, and engaged by ſo many promiſes; wherein it is impoſsible for him to deny himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eleventhly, Further alſo hence wee may learn <hi>how to deale with thoſe in affliction in whatſoever Caſe:</hi> View them well firſt, be not too brief with them; Heare them vent themſelves, Try the ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes and pulſes of their diſeaſe,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:116556:94"/>as <hi>Iobs</hi> three friends who ſate (it is written) ſeven dayes and nights ſilent, becauſe thay ſaw his griefe was great; for <hi>unſeaſonable comforts are and prove but like raine falling upon hard ſtones, which runs off as faſt as it comes, making no impreſsions:</hi> whilſt their buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing heads and tranſported ſpirits are gadding, plodding elſewhere with ſtrong diverſions; as it fell out with this good Gentlewomen; who paſſed not for all was ſaid unto her for a long time, neither was hope of cure, untill the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils counſell was bewrayed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Therefore, it behoves to be circumſpect and patient awhile to finde out the cauſe and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of diſtempers, or elſe no good can bee done; for though <hi>counſell in the heart of a man be like deep waters,</hi> yet <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:116556:95"/>ſhewes, that a man of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will fetch it out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And then his counſell being bewrayed, the Patient muſt be mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, meekly and gently uſed, not hald and puld, hurried and chid; O no, this is a wrong courſe; but uſed with abundant patience and love, waited upon, with many good words, and ſuffered to bemoane themſelves as much as they liſt, repeating one thing ſtill over and over againe, as often as they pleaſe; Many good things fit for them muſt be uttered in their hearing not too ſoone preſſd upon them, as ſpoken unto others; they muſt have here a little and there a little, not preſſd beyond their ſtrength; wonne by degrees with a loving ſweet affable car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; as all theſe yeares of this good womans trouble ſhee was
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:116556:95"/>ſerved by all her friends which wonne much , and wrung many things from her in love which could not otherwiſe poſſibly have been attained: For alas, <hi>All that while they are in a ſpirituall fever; and what and Phyſitian will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to give phyſick in a burning fever?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When they begin to mend and become more docible, wee muſt no then bring like <hi>Iobs</hi> friends (who miſtook his caſe) the Law for the Goſpel. This is Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans work uſually, moſt of them are to apt to lay too much load upon themſelves; It is an eaſie matter to throw down, when one is a going <hi>(facilis diſcenſus Averni)</hi> then it is Satans work, down with it, down with it, down with it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the ground: <hi>O, but it is the work of the great God to raiſe
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:116556:96"/>one up who is dejected:</hi> It is the work of the Holy Ghoſt in that caſe to raiſe up, encourage, and convince us in a deſpairing eſtate: Wherefore ſpirituall Phyſitians muſt be like Chriſt the great Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>A bruiſed reed ſhall hee not break, and ſmoaking flax ſhall he not quench, untill hee bring forth judgement unto victory,</hi> or a victorious ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification in us: as wee were glad to doe by this good creature, by all gentle meanes to toll on, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and cheriſh her ſpirit, untill God at length came in, and did all.</p>
            <p>Twelfly, But lo, lo, whilſt we are now towards a concluſion, where <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> alſo appeareth, in treating on the paſſages of this <hi>Rare Caſe</hi> not to be forgotten, ſo as the ſtupidi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, dulneſſe, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:116556:96"/>and ſluggiſhneſſe of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpoſitions might be whetted and ſet on edge more then ever thereby unto more exact and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous frequent actings thereof; <hi>for our freedome from thoſe innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble troubles, ſorrowes, ſickneſſes and diſeaſes, both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, of all ſorts, which tormenteth many others better then we; who enjoying abundance of unpercei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ordinary mercies, doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſlight and neglect the ſame:</hi> For, when vexations of tooth-ach, ſtone, ſtrangury, convulſions, gout, palſies, burning, fevers, agues, ulcers, ſwellings, broken and diſ-joynted bones, ſtreined ſinews, diſplaced arteries, inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations and the like annoy us; terrors of conſcience, with a wounded ſpirit; Satans inceſſant buffettings, apprehenſions of Hell,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:116556:97"/>and the wrath of God affright us: O what torments, dolefull dayes and miſeries doe we endure, to bec as it is, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>In per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall feares, having no aſſurance of our lives?</hi> And yet O how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull are wee and ſenſleſſe of ſo great and wonderfull mercies, as daily and nightly we are freed from, the leaſt whereof (when their contraries ſurprize us) makes us cry out as moſt miſerable: witneſſe this good Gentlewoman fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, <hi>Who being and living in continuall feares, valued nothing at all this world, took no comfort in any thing here below:</hi> And yet it is ſtrange how daily we ſlubber over our <hi>Thanksgivings</hi> and freedom from miſeries we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, as though they were not moſt great and wonderfull, every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning renewed mercies; or elſe we
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:116556:97"/>ſhould have wonderfull and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dayes: But it is our miſery and frailty, that a prick of a pin in our fleſh uſually wee are more ſenſible of, then of the health and harmonicall concord both of ſoul and body: And therefore hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to chafe, ſurvey, and conſider of our preſent mercies, to bruiſe and toſſe them, as men doe <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick ſweets,</hi> that their fragran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies may the more abundantly ſpread forth themſelves, whilſt the <hi>North and South</hi> winde of the ſpirit thus blowes upon them, to ſhew forth and make us conſider of their excellencies unto Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations utmoſt wonder; thus to aſcend a higher pitch upon this <hi>mount of Thanksgiving,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more perfect upon earth of our endleſſe work in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:116556:98"/>
            <p>Thirteenthly, As we began with this good Creature, who led forth the <hi>Van</hi> in a <hi>Tempeſt;</hi> ſo now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been victorious, let us ſo far honour her as to <hi>bring up the Reere,</hi> and make the <hi>laſt Uſe,</hi> which ſhe her ſelfe made unto all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Survivers howſoever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, eſpecially, by <hi>diſſertion</hi> or <hi>hardneſſe</hi> of <hi>Heart: That they ſhould upon experience of her</hi> CASE, <hi>and Gods goodneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, not be ſo diſcouraged in any eſtate whatſoever, as to give over the uſe of meanes, but to ply them ſtill; truſt and wait, and they would prevaile at length.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then from hence, let all ſuch learn to wait and depend upon God: <hi>And ſince</hi> (as it is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.) <hi>hee waits in all their troubles for an opportunity to ſhew mercy unto them; therefore to wait and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:116556:98"/>upon him untill hee come:</hi> For though they may wait long, yet herein they may abundantly comfort themſelves, That God will comfort them according to all the dayes they have beene af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and the years wherein they have ſeene evill; That hee who hath ſhewed us ſore and great troubles, will yet quicken us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and bring us up from the depth of the earth; encreaſe our greatneſſe, and comfort us on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſide, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.20.21. That though they have beene led through fire and water, cauſing men ride over their heads, yet that he will bring them forth unto a wealthy place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.12. That when they walk in the midſt of trouble, God will revive them, and maintaine their cauſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.12. That after deliverances
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:116556:99"/>from affliction, their ſouls ſhall be as a watered Garden, and ſhall not ſorrow any more at all, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.12. And that in deliverance, they ſhall have ſeverall comforts, anſwering their ſeverall croſſes, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.8. being built up againe, as at the firſt, <hi>Ier.</hi> 33.7.</p>
            <p>And therefore to perſiſt and goe on, truſting ſtill and depending upon God; becauſe though they may for the preſent want ſenſe and feeling of Gods love; yet (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks) becauſe in the interim they are kept by the power of God unto ſalvation, that they are all in Gods hand at the worſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3. from above having the eternall God for their refuge; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath being claſpt in his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting armes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.27. And ſo, <hi>Becauſe hee brings light from darkneſſe, perfection from weakneſſe,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:116556:99"/>by death bringing unto life, and by the gates of Hell unto Heaven:</hi> Seeing he makes all things work together for good unto us, and all his works (how croſſes ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) beautifull in time. O let the Saints after ſo rare a Preſident of this good woman, never here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after bee out of Heart, aſſuring themſelves of deliverance whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their Caſe be, in uſing of the meanes: For, <hi>What is a hard heart, yea ten thouſand hard hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that great God, who with a Word made Heaven and Earth? for whom nothing is too hard, Gen.</hi> 17.1. Who over-turneth the Mountaines by the roots, who ſhakes the Earth; Heaven drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at his preſence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.8. who calleth all the Stars by their names; by the greatneſſe of his might, ſpans the Heavens, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:116556:100"/>them with blackneſſe, making Sack-cloth their covering; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Sun not to riſe, and ſealing up the Starres, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Upon all theſe grounds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and many moe (too tedious to relate) <hi>let all ſtoope unto God, Saint-like lie and ſit down at his feet, receiving of his words,</hi> taking the experimentall counſell of this good woman, to keep cloſe unto God in the uſe of meanes, and then they are ſafe, <hi>Reſolving that though they die, yet to die at his feet;</hi> and ſo to wait, and truſt ſtill unto the laſt, for he will come at laſt unto them; as Habacuc hath it, <hi>The viſion is for an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, though it it tarry, yet wait, for it will come and not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> as it did unto this good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man after ten years expectation, whoſe abundant feeling and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:116556:100"/>in the end, did manifoldly ſurmount all her ſufferings and troubles in an unſpeakable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and meaſure, leaving her ſelfe as <hi>the matchleſse monument of Gods unſpeakeable mercy, unto all ſtout, ſtiffe, and hard-hearted ſinners for ever, even though for a while they doe reſiſt the meanes;</hi> who for all this may be won by overcomming mercies as ſhe was; ſo tryumphing over all their ſpirituall enemies, as to ſing at length in a more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting and lofty way with <hi>Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Judg. 5.21.</bibl> O my Soule! thou haſt trodden down ſtrength.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 52. 1. 9.</hi> for kn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead</hi> known <hi>p. 138. l. 2<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> for ſtrangely, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. ſuddenly. <hi>p. 131.</hi> for Mr, <hi>r.</hi> Miſtriſſe. <hi>p. 162. l. 13.</hi> for fell ſleep, <hi>r.</hi> had ſlept.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
